<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-05T08:10:49-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jayaram Hariharan</title><subtitle>Jayaram Hariharan's personal website.</subtitle><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><entry><title type="html">2022-04-05</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-05" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-05" /><published>2022-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-05">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 5, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;becoming-an-expert&quot;&gt;Becoming an Expert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time trying to be as environmentally friendly as possible.
For example I don’t just toss things into recycling, I wash them out, and
sort them by the material type. I maintain a compost pile to allow natural
material to compost. I even take timed (short) showers every other day to
conserve water. At what point (if any) am I an environmental expert?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Green&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like you’re quite green indeed! Interesting question, makes me want to
know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you want to be an “expert” at all. Does it matter how other people
perceive your environmental credentials? Are you looking to obtain a job or
pivot to a role that is in the environmental space? If your goal is at all
related to your profession, then I suspect there will be limits to how far
your environmental actions in your personal life can take you. Generally for
professional advancement it is more advantageous to either have educational
credentials in the field, or have on-the-job experience, which you could obtain
at any level within the target industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job-stuff aside, if you simply want to brag to your friends and family about
how environmental you are, then I suppose this question is a bit simpler. The
idea of being an “expert” is a bit vague and hard to pin down, as you’ve
realized. Especially for something like being “environmentally-friendly,” as
our understanding of the environment and climate is steadily evolving. There is
the popular “10,000 hours makes you an expert” line of thinking, which I
believe was proposed by Malcolm Gladwell. So maybe you should estimate the
hours you dedicate to your environmental behaviors, and once they tally up to
about 10,000 hours, you can just start calling yourself an environmental
expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay clean,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flexin&quot;&gt;Flexin’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;To be candid, things have been going pretty well for me recently. After a
few years of regular exercise, I am feeling pretty fit and trim. I have
just moved into a new job that is much more rewarding in all aspects, which
is also making me happier. However I realize that right now, as well as for
the past few years, things have not been going so well for many people. So,
in a sense I think I feel a bit guilty about my successes and my happiness.
How can I enjoy my life without this guilt? I don’t try to go around rubbing
my happiness in other peoples’ faces, but sometimes I feel like I am just
flexing unnecessarily when I talk about how well work is going, or how
great I feel after a workout. Have any advice for me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Flexosaurus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flexosaurus,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow you sound like such a nice person! It is truly very considerate of you to
keep other peoples’ experiences in your thoughts even as things are going so
well for you. Unless you are walking around boasting about your life, I don’t
think you really have anything to worry about, and it doesn’t sound like you
do much bragging. If you feel like you are in a good place, and have the
time to spare, it might be fulfilling for you to volunteer in your community.
When you volunteer, you can contribute to bringing happiness into the lives
of people in your community who may not currently be in as privileged a
position as you are. Even if you want to volunteer and help clean up a park, an
activity that does not require direct interaction with others, as you pick up
litter you may think to yourself that some person will visit the park later
and have a better experience because they didn’t have to look at trash. So my
advice is simple, just try to be proactive and give back if you are feeling
guilty about your happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Environment" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Success" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 5, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-03-20</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-20" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-03-20" /><published>2022-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-20">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on March 20, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;freezer-burn&quot;&gt;Freezer Burn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I opened up my freezer to a bunch of food with freezer burn on it. Do you know its still safe to eat? How can I prevent this from happening in the future? Sorry for such a basic question, but this is where I find myself today.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Burnt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnt,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello. Freezer burn is less than ideal for sure, but at least you should feel
some relief when you learn that the food should still be safe to consume. My
understanding of freezer burn is that it is simply what happens when frozen
food begins to thaw, and moisture begins to escape the food and re-freezes on
its exterior. For this reason, freezer burn changes the texture of the food
(usually negatively), but does not indicate that the food has spoiled. However,
if you had a power outage and food totally thawed and re-froze, it is possible
things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; spoil when you lost power. So just be careful / aware of how the
freezer burn came about. Typically, I’ve found my items in the freezer can end
up with some freezer burn after they’ve sat in the freezer for a long time,
in these cases I assume the opening and closing of the door over time caused
moisture to escape and re-freeze, or is introduced from outside to create the
freezer burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay frosty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gaps-between-classes&quot;&gt;Gaps Between Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am in my first year of college and am having trouble making the most of my time in between classes. I have some gaps between different lectures of varying lengths, sometimes I have an hour, sometimes I have three, but I struggle with what I should be doing during these free periods. In high school I never had this type of free time in the middle of the day besides my lunch period. What do you recommend I do? Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Gap for Kids&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gap,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair question, it is an interesting situation you may find yourself in for the
rest of your collegiate career. There are a number of different things people
do with their mid-day gaps, some of which I am sure you may be familiar with,
but others that may be novel to you. Some ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare for your next class by reviewing or reading ahead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you live close by, go back home and eat or do some housework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Swing by the gym and get a workout in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find an on-campus job and schedule shifts during your longer breaks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a position as a lab assistant - some tasks like washing dishes in a wet lab don’t require close supervision so you can likely do that when you have free time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join a club and become involved in it’s running, some may have offices and administrative tasks that need to be taken care of during the day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit the library and read a book&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eat some lunch or a snack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the weather is good, find a nice spot to take a nap outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the weather is bad, there may be designated nap spots on campus (I don’t know if this is actually true)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take your pick, some of those suggestions are certainly better than others.
But different things work for different people, so just try to figure out what
works best for you. Best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="School" /><summary type="html">Advice given on March 20, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-03-11</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-11" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-03-11" /><published>2022-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-11">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on March 11, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gracefully-taking-a-compliment&quot;&gt;Gracefully Taking A Compliment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I was wondering if you could give me some advice on how to gracefully accept
compliments. I am lucky enough to be surrounded by such kind people, but I
feel so awkward when someone gives me a compliment. I tend to freeze up a bit
and say something like “thank you, you’re too kind”. But this feels so
strange, so any suggestions you have on how I could improve the way I receive
compliments would be much appreciated. To clarify, I am talking about
work-related compliments along the lines of “great work on X” or “this
report was really useful,” as opposed to those related to my style or taste
in movies (both of which I have no problems accepting compliments about).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Grace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grace,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is such a nice situation to be in. Clearly you are not so awkward about
receiving compliments that people have decided to stop complimenting you on
your work! Humbly, I will say I personally don’t receive a ton of compliments,
but I think I can still offer you some advice. It sounds like you are a bit
bashful about the compliments, maybe because you feel they are undeserved or
too much for the effort or work you put in. I think the first step to getting
around this awkwardness is understanding that people do not compliment you
out of obligation; compliments are almost always voluntary and genuinely
meant. If someone is giving you a compliment, even if it is for something
small to you, it may mean something more to them. Once you internalize this
fact, it may be easier to understand the value you are providing to your
coworkers, and subsequently it may be easier to accept their compliments.
The one thing you should not do in this kind of a work setting is downplay the
work and say something like “oh thanks, it was nothing”. Then your coworkers
might start to take your effort and work for granted. I think a short and
simple, “thank you, I’m glad you found it helpful” or similar is the best way
to respectfully acknowledge this type of a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the great question,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sorry-machine&quot;&gt;Sorry Machine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I think I am a serial apologizer. I find myself constantly saying “sorry” or
apologizing for minor inconveniences, or sometimes apologizing for things
that are neither inconveniences nor in my control to begin with. Last week it
rained and I caught myself apologizing to someone for the weather! As if
I could do anything about that! How can I stop being such a sorry machine?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Apologizer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologizer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is good to be apologetic in some situations, but I agree with you, it is
certainly possible to apologize too much. This is a bit of an unfortunate
habit you’ve gotten yourself into. I think this habit, like any other, is a
bit difficult to break. Step one might be slowing down the pace at which you
speak and taking a pause to think before you say something. Maybe you’ve
avoided the all-too-common “likes,” “ums,” and other filler words with your
“sorrys” and other apologies. Generally, I think the easiest way to break any
speaking habit is to speak more slowly and carefully consider your words before
you say them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Manners" /><summary type="html">Advice given on March 11, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-02-28</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-28" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-02-28" /><published>2022-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-28">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on February 28, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harsh-words-make-me-sad&quot;&gt;Harsh Words Make Me Sad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a problem at work, but I’m not sure if it is a “me” problem, or a
larger problem with the workplace culture. When my manager criticizes my
work, I feel really sad. Fortunately, I know I am not the only one who’s
work gets critiqued - I believe this type of criticism is leveled at all of
my co-workers in equal measure. However I don’t get the impression it fazes
them, while I usually need to take a few minutes to re-focus and center
myself before I can continue my day. Am I just too soft? Is this an actual
problem or am I just dramatic? Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shaken Up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaken,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s okay to be sensitive. Without the details it is hard to gauge whether or
not you are too sensitive, however. If your office is a bit larger, try to
get a sense for how other managers provide feedback to their teams. The wording
you provide, “criticism”, and “critique”, are a bit harsher than what I’d
expect, a more positive workplace culture might have you using a word
like “feedback” to describe the comments you get about your work from a
manager. If you are comfortable confiding in any of your immediate coworkers,
you might want to ask them if they ever feel your manager’s comments are too
harsh. Their answer could let you know if your feelings are shared by others,
or if indeed you are overly sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My admittedly harsh take, is that this is likely a good growing and learning
experience for you. You’ve gotten stuck in an uncomfortable situation, and it
is smart of you to be trying to sort this out. Whether or not your fellow
co-workers think your manager is too hard on y’all is almost unimportant; how
you, as an individual, handle it is what matters most. You are unlikely to get
your supervisor to change their ways, and it doesn’t seem like a productive use
of time to try. It is more practical for you to either change your state of
mind and accept that they are a bit more harsh than you’d like, or start
figuring out how to remove yourself from the situation. I am assuming that your
manager is otherwise a good colleague and coworker, and really this is the only
sticking point you have with them. So given those ideas, you should weigh your
options and think about your job, your career, and your life in a bigger
picture sense, to determine what the best course of action for you in this
situation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;afraid-to-fall&quot;&gt;Afraid to Fall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve recently had a few health scares and am a bit wary of many physical
activities now. My doctors all say I can get back to life as usual, but I
feel like I have a mental block, and I can’t get over my fears. Do you have
any suggestions to help me get back to living an exciting and active life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,
Nervous Nellie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Nellie,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I can’t pretend to know the details of your exact situation, I can’t help
but think that your reaction is totally normal. If you haven’t already brought
up this mental challenge you’re facing to your doctors, I’d suggest you do that
first, as I am not a medical professional. They may have some good suggestions,
or may be able to refer you to a therapist or psychiatrist that can help you
get over your mental hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think you’ve had enough of doctors’ offices, I guess my suggestion would
be to take things one day at a time. While you will have to push yourself a
little bit outside of your comfort zone to get back to what you used to do,
don’t be upset if progress is slow and incremental. These things take time, and
you certainly don’t want to create a new physical or mental problem for
yourself. So just take things slow, and progress at your own rate, and know
that what you are feeling is totally understandable, I think most people would
be hesitant to resume activities that were previously perilous to them!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Criticism" /><category term="Courage" /><summary type="html">Advice given on February 28, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-02-10</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-02-10" /><published>2022-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-10">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on February 10, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unsolicited-advice-on-graduate-school&quot;&gt;Unsolicited Advice on Graduate School&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello folks, this week I am departing from the usual advice column to provide
some (partially) unsolicited advice on graduate school.
I am going to attempt to distill the advice I seem to give on a semi-annual
basis to strangers and acquaintances who are choosing a graduate program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to break this into 3 parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should you go to graduate school?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to identify potential schools, programs, and advisors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to keep in mind while in school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-should-you-go-to-graduate-school&quot;&gt;1. Should you go to graduate school?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this is an incredibly personal decision, and many personal factors
may enhance or limit your ability to attend graduate school in the first place.
Independent of those factors, I think it is necessary to identify &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you
want to go to graduate school. There are many reasons, but you need to be sure
that you find a compelling one. If you cannot find a strong reason to go, you
are likely to struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to keep in mind when making this decision are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are my current opportunities in the workforce? Is school more
attractive than any of these options?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is my financial situation? Graduate school is rarely a time during
which you will be able to accumulate wealth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What opportunities do I wish to have in the future? Can graduate school
help unlock these, or would I be better off finding a job that provides me
with relevant work experience for my dream career?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I feel about doing homework and taking exams? These are largely
unavoidable when you go to school.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Am I willing to spend significant amounts of time reading and writing? No
matter the field of study, you will likely spend large amounts of time
both reading and writing as most graduate degrees culminate in a thesis
or dissertation (and maybe some research publications along the way).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-how-to-identify-potential-schools-programs-and-advisors&quot;&gt;2. How to identify potential schools, programs, and advisors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have decided to go to graduate school, the next decision is to
identify specific schools and programs to apply to. Then, depending on which
you are accepted to, you have to decide which to attend. So what makes for a
good fit between a prospective student and a particular research group?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional advice is to search for a program in which you feel accepted. A
place where you feel welcomed by the faculty and other graduate students, as
these people will be your professors and peers for a number of years. This
is certainly great advice! It is typically accompanied by the (obvious)
suggestion that the group you join should be doing research you are
interested in, and would like to conduct. All of this advice is totally sound,
but I think there are additional elements many people forget to consider (at
least I did), which are worth thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first has to do with the school itself, what is its reputation? Where is
it? While these factors can be relatively unimportant if the specific program
you are applying to is incredibly well known at the institution, having an
understanding of how the rest of the world and country perceive the institution
is important. If you end up job searching outside of your field, the prestige
of the university will supersede the reputation of your graduate program. The
location of the university may impact where graduates tend to work; some
schools have well established reputations and pipelines to jobs at regional
companies and agencies. If you know what type of career you plan to pursue
after school, then you should see whether the school you are considering has
many alumni in those type of roles at the specific companies or institutions
you would like to one day work at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second, has to do with the specific graduate program, and basically
involves the same question. What is its reputation in the field? Most
university departments are quite broad relative to individual lab research
sub-disciplines and specialties. It is important to ensure the program you
attend has some expertise in the sub-field you are interested in.
To get a feel for this, you should browse the department’s
website and visit individual faculty pages to see what their research focus is
in. This way you can see if your research interests align broadly with the
research the department is conducting. The prestige of the department or
program itself is important to consider if you are looking to work in the field
after graduating. You might be surprised to learn about the relatively small or
unknown schools across the globe which are highly regarded in your field. To
gauge that type of prestige, I suggest you look up some manuscripts in your
desired field of study, and look through the references to find the labs or
institutions which appear frequently. This is one indicator of how established
an individual department is in the field. Another method of identifying these
programs is to talk to someone you know, preferably someone not in academia,
about the field to try and learn whether or not there are a handful of programs
you should definitely be considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third, and final consideration is arguably the most important, and that is
the selection of a research group and advisor. Now do not forget, this is
definitely a 2-way street, as prospective students search for a good fit with
a lab, advisors search for their newest advisee. As a prospective student, you
should search for a lab which does research that you are interested in, this
is something you cannot really be flexible on. This step should greatly shrink
the number of potential research groups within your broader scientific field.
Standard advice from here is to suggest you get in touch with the PI of the
lab, try to speak with them and see if you are likely to get along, and then
try to speak with some current students to understand what the student
experience in the lab group and in the graduate program is like. Beyond these
steps, which are incredibly important, I think there are a few further
considerations worth making. How long do students typically stay in this
group? Another way of putting that is: how long is the typical degree for a
member of this group? What do students of this research group tend to go do
after they graduate? What skills do students of this group obtain and leave
with? Is there an expectation to publish, if so, how successful are students
in publishing? Is the group highly collaborative with other researchers within
or external to the university? Are students involved in these collaborations?
I think most of these questions can be posed to current graduate students when
you speak with them about joining the group. However, I also think you should
do some of this investigation for yourself, as each individual is going to
present you with a biased version of what they experienced. To do this, you
might examine the research group website (if there is one) to try and see
how long students seem to be there, and what alumni of the group end up doing.
Fortunately for you, senior graduate students are likely searching for jobs
themselves, and I think that it is increasingly common for them to have some
sort of web-presence, where you may be able to see their C.V. or learn more
about their graduate experience. I think this type of investigation on the
part of the prospective student can be very beneficial, as this will help you
understand what experiences or opportunities may be available, and what skills
you will exit the group having. To understand the publishing habits of the
group, I would look up the PI on Google Scholar. This should give you an
indication of how frequent they publish, who common collaborators are,
and roughly what the expectations for publishing are for students of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-what-to-keep-in-mind-while-in-school&quot;&gt;3. What to keep in mind while in school&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in school your primary focus should be on completing the objectives
required to complete your degree requirements and graduate. However, I would
caution against having a myopic focus on these objectives, as the requirements
for obtaining a degree may not directly align with the qualifications
necessary to begin your dream career. The alignment of graduate program
requirements with job requirements will vary based on your field, as well as
your target career. Even so, I think all students should keep these cautionary
words in the back of their minds. Students who wish to become professors in the
future, for example, should not lose track of the facets of professorship
beyond research, such as teaching, and proposal writing. These prospective
professors should do what they can to gain experience teaching, designing
course curricula, and writing proposals as much as they can while graduate
students, to improve the quality of their future academic applications. That is
just one example, for students eyeing careers in industry, it is worth looking
up job advertisements to understand the skills employers are looking for. These
may or may not match the skills you are developing as a student, and some may
be technical skills you can learn in courses, or incorporate into some aspect
of your graduate work. I’d encourage future and current students to take the
time to make this evaluation at least semi-annually if not on a quarterly
basis so that there is time to make small adjustments and find opportunities
while in school that can ultimately increase the quality of your future job
applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember that your graduate school experience comes down to what you
are able to get out of it. Nobody can care about or prioritize your experience
more than you can. I went to a talk about graduate school once where the
professor giving the lecture reminded everyone that they are just a single
student of many in their supervisor’s lab group - and as such, you must be
your own best advocate. It doesn’t matter how supportive or well-meaning your
professors and peers are, the onus is on the individual to get what they need
to get done, even if it means pestering people when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this rambling piece of advice is able to help at least 1 person
better navigate their graduate school experience. The standard advice column
will be back next time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Unsolicited" /><category term="Graduate School" /><summary type="html">Advice given on February 10, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-02-04</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-04" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-02-04" /><published>2022-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-04">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on February 4, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-the-will-to-exercise&quot;&gt;Finding the Will to Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;While it is winter, I can’t help but think ahead to the summer. When I do so,
I realize I’m not in the physical shape I wish I was in. While I don’t know you
personally, I get the impression you are reasonably fit and stay in shape.
So that being said, I’m hoping you can give me some advice on how to motivate
myself to exercise. If it helps any, I am hoping to run more, as I would like
to spend more time outside. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Bugs Runny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs Runny,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well one option is to imagine someone is hunting you down like a rabbit! But
maybe I can try to provide some more realistic advice as well. Personally, I
have found that identifying an end goal or objective for an activity can help
me find the motivation needed to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to run a marathon, it is helpful to find a training
plan, and stick to it, to increase your chances of success. You’ve vaguely
mentioned wanting to be in some sort of physical shape, but I would encourage
you to more specifically define the end goal. Once you’ve done that, you can
break up the overall objective into smaller milestones, and chart yourself a
realistic path to achieving each one of them. If you are aiming for a target
weight on the scale, maybe define your ultimate goal, and then set intermediate
targets. This gives you the opportunity to track your progress, and adjust the
overall timeline if you find you are unable to drop the pounds at the rate
you wanted to. This is normal! If you cannot hit the targets you set, it is not
indicative of failure to act or improve yourself, it may just mean you’ve set
unrealistic or unachievable timelines for your goals. So I wouldn’t get
discouraged if you miss a self-identified milestone, if it happens multiple
times, I would just step back and maybe re-adjust your overall timeline to
match what is physically feasible for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the daily or weekly level, you need to think about how your actions and
decisions will impact your future self. If we think about being in shape by
the summertime, that may sound like it is far away as it is only February now.
But, how long does it take to get into shape? If you aren’t actively trying to
improve your physical fitness, maybe you’ll even slide further from being in
shape between now and the summer. The decision to go on a run today is a small
but incremental step in the direction you want to head. So just remember to
keep the overall time horizons in perspective, and think about future you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;re-oat-milk&quot;&gt;Re: Oat Milk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I saw your advice last week regarding oat milk. I agree that Oatly is pretty
good. As someone who has been on a lactose-free diet for a long time, I just
wanted to also point your reader to soy milk as a potential alternative.
In particular, I have gotten used to the Silk brand of soy milk and would
recommend that to your reader. Silk has been making alternative milks for a
while, and I would suggest trying their almond and oat milks as well as the
soy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the tip! Hopefully last week’s advice seeker sees this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Motivation" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Well-Being" /><summary type="html">Advice given on February 4, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-01-28</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-28" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-01-28" /><published>2022-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-28">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on January 28, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;avocado-pizza&quot;&gt;Avocado Pizza?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I went over a friend’s house to make some pizza and hang out. Naturally we
had to discuss pizza toppings. He proposed we top our pizza with avocado of
all things. This sounded absurd to me, so I figured he was joking and I went
along with it - “yeah dude totally” (or something like that). When he actually
grabbed an avocado and started slicing it up, I realized it wasn’t a joke. Now
I like an avocado as much as the next person, or so I thought, but I wasn’t
prepared to have it on pizza. When I told my friend I was joking, and I’d never
eat avocado on pizza he got offended. I told him avocado on pizza was
ridiculous, and this didn’t go over well. Kinda put a damper on our chill
evening, so I’d like to smooth this over.
How can I convince my friend I’m not a pizza topping snob?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Papa Guac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Papa Guac,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well you’ve gotten yourself into a cheesy mess here. I can confess to having
eaten pizza with avocado as a topping before. I will say that I have not
repeated the experience since, as the avocado didn’t improve the quality of my
slice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experiences with avocado on pizza aside, I don’t know how big of a problem
this is. If your friend seems overly touchy after this experience, maybe you
should open up about one of your weird food habits, we’ve all got them after
all. But I am optimistic that a genuine apology will resolve this issue.
Maybe offer to bring over guacamole and chips to snack on the next time you
both have a pizza night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humbly yours,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oat-milk&quot;&gt;Oat Milk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve recently found out that I am lactose intolerant and would like to switch
from dairy milk to an alternative product. I have heard a lot about oat milk
in recent years, and was wondering - what do you think of oat milk? Do you have
a favorite brand?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Lactase-less&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lactase-less,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are unhappy with this recent turn of events, I would like to reassure
you that plenty of people are lactose intolerant or lactose sensitive, so you
definitely have company in that regard. I’ll briefly mention that oat milk is
not the only kind of dairy milk alternative, so you aren’t stuck with oat milk
if you find you dislike the taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, to your question, I have indeed had oat milk and I find it to be
quite nice. I’ve had it with coffee, and I’ve also sipped plain oat milk.
However, I am far from an oat milk connoisseur; I think I’ve only had 2
different brands of the stuff. The first oat milk I had was produced by Oatly,
one of the leaders in the oat milk space. I tried them based on a friend’s
recommendation, and I do think that Oatly is the GOATly (greatest of all time).
Their oat milk is capable of frothing up nicely in a coffee, and has a similar
body and consistency to dairy milk. As I’m located in central Texas at the
moment, I have also tried the HEB (a regional grocery chain) brand oat milk.
Honestly, no complains about their version either. I believe Oatly is available
across Europe and the US at this point, so I definitely recommend trying them
out. If you’ve got access to HEB, I’d say you should try theirs too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I’m off to contact Oatly about doing some marketing for them with this
new “Oatly the GOATly” slogan I’ve coined. Hope this was slightly helpful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Well-Being" /><summary type="html">Advice given on January 28, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-01-19</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-19" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-01-19" /><published>2022-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-19">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on January 19, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cranky-comrade&quot;&gt;Cranky Comrade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So I’ve started telling this funny joke at work now that the new year has
rolled around. This joke is totally a classic, and I enjoy making it every
January. Basically, when some topic, task, or activity comes up in
conversation and I haven’t yet done it in January, I say something along the
lines of, “hm, well I haven’t done &lt;insert activity=&quot;&quot;&gt; since last year!&quot;&lt;/insert&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now, as I’m sure you understand, that type of comedy is both hilarious and
never gets old. Well my co-worker/friend seems to disagree. He just told
me to knock it off and that it is a terrible joke. What should I do? I really
thought I was being hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Funny Guy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FG,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well it is better to hear this criticism from a friend than your boss or
just an acquaintance at the office. But yeah, I agree with your friend, the
joke probably isn’t funny beyond the first or second telling each year. So I’d
suggest you apologize to your friend, and limit your annual telling of this
wise-crack to one or two instances per year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laughingly yours,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on January 19, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-01-12</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-12" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-01-12" /><published>2022-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-12">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on January 12, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;these-bros-aint-loyal&quot;&gt;These Bros ain’t loyal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve got a bit of a familial problem on my hands. If you’ve read the subject
line you know where this is going. My brothers are stirring up trouble for me!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It all started just before last Thanksgiving, when I told my parents I was not
coming home for our annual family get together. Now I cited concerns about
COVID, which are of course valid, but were not actually my true concerns, as I
work from home. Nay, my true concern was that my parents would give me
never-ending grief over my latest tattoo, a dragon which winds around my left
forearm. For context, my parents are straight-edged, anti-tattoo people, and
have struggled to come to terms with my more liberal inclinations. I figured
skipping Thanksgiving would just let me avoid dealing with this problem. Next,
when Christmas came around, we were in the midst of another COVID wave of
infections, so I used this as an excuse to skip the end of the year family
gathering once more. At this point I was feeling pretty smug, and mentioned how
happy I was about this strategy to one of my brothers. This turned out to be
a grave mistake. My brother ratted me out to my entire family! He not only
mentioned the tattoo, but told everyone I was avoiding family gatherings just
so I wouldn’t have to speak with them all about the tattoo. The rest of my
brothers ganged up on me and our family group chat exploded with messages about
how awful I was behaving.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now I can admit that I certainly didn’t make the best choices, but I didn’t
expect to be raked over the coals like this, by my own brothers, no less. So
what should I do? How should I even feel? I always thought I could count on my
brothers as confidants, but now I’m no longer so sure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Broseph&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broseph,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve left me at a bit of a loss for words. I don’t know your family, or your
relationship with your brothers and parents, but it sounds like you need to
think about those relationships. I can’t help but wonder if your brother spilt
the beans and everyone else jumped on because they missed seeing you during the
holidays. Maybe they were hurt by what you’d done, and didn’t really care about
the tattoo after all. You never mentioned your brothers’ stance on tattoos, so
I could imagine them being upset if they didn’t see you all because of your
parents’ opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think you need to have an honest conversation with your parents about who you
are and how their words and actions have bothered you enough that you skipped
seeing them rather than letting them see your tattoo. Similarly, I think you
need to speak with your brothers, and resolve this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deriving-me-crazy&quot;&gt;Deriving me crazy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve just started a new job, and one of my co-workers is driving me crazy. Or
maybe I should say he’s “deriving” me crazy (ha ha). Let me explain, I am a
statistician, so math is part of the job. In my new role, I’m working as part
of a small team to conduct statistical analysis of customer data given to us
by our clients. This project has been ongoing for several years now, so there
are many unwritten procedures associated with how we handle this data. As a
result, I frequently check in with my colleague “Jerry”, to make sure I am not
making an incorrect assumption or performing an invalid procedure because of
some undocumented property or attribute. The first few times I did this,
Jerry would jump into a fundamental explanation of the statistical method or
technique. He seemed to interpret my question as one about statistics, rather
than a simple question about the attributes of our data. After the first few
instances of this, I spoke with him directly about the manner to let him know
my questions were about the data, not the statistics. I said I would make it
clear if/when I have any doubts about statistical methods, but otherwise I am
an adept statistician. Jerry took this well, and things improved for the rest
of the week. After the weekend however, Jerry was right back to his old ways
and gave me long, slightly condescending lectures whenever I asked a question.
What should I do to resolve this issue? I cannot work like this.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Random Variable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R.V.,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yikes! This sounds like an issue for sure. Well this is a new job, so it seems
safe to assume that you are an employable person. This is surely not a
sustainable work environment for you in the long-term. I honestly think you’ve
done your fair share of polite work by trying to resolve the matter directly
with Jerry. Now I think you can slightly escalate this issue as you seek a
solution. If the company is mid-to-large-sized, I think you should try to see
if you can transfer to another team. I’d like to imagine Jerry’s aren’t present
on every team at the company. Now, if this is not feasible, or if it will take
much longer than you can bear, I think it is reasonable to speak with your
immediate manager. You sound like a very reasonable person, and it seems like
Jerry means well? So if you believe that is the case, I don’t think you want to
complain, necessarily, but rather raise this as an issue which is continuing,
and see if your supervisor can offer any suggestions or solutions. Ideally,
they will understand your plight and speak politely but firmly with Jerry
separately. You can also approach HR if your company has an HR department to
see what suggestions they might have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, if none of those options work, I think you should just start looking
for another job. You’ve just started at this company, and I can’t believe this
is the type of experience you were looking for. If none of the above options
work, then maybe the company is just not worth working for; the problem you’ve
described sounds like a real issue, and a supportive company culture would
resolve the matter in an efficient and fair way. So that being said,
statisticians are valued in many different industries and in many different
companies, so I would say that it is worth looking for an exit. In interviews,
I think you can be honest about the issue you are having, and if you outline
the steps you’ve taken to resolve the problem before you started looking for
other work, you should come across as a very reasonable person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on January 12, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-01-05</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-05" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-01-05" /><published>2022-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-01-05">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on January 5, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risk-tolerance-and-relationships&quot;&gt;Risk (Tolerance) and Relationships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve got a relationship problem I am hoping you can help resolve. My partner
and I have very different perceptions and tolerances for risk. I know I am
fairly risk-averse, but I had no idea my partner was such a risk-seeker. With
the pandemic raging on for so long, my partner has been very
accepting and cooperative with my requests to be safe, and I appreciate that.
But now that it has been almost 2 years, we are both starting to get out and
do more things which is where the problems are beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For example, the other night we were sitting on the couch and she was
browsing for motorcycles online. When I asked if she was considering getting
one, she said ‘yeah, it would be so much fun to ride out on the open road.’
Now, I think motorcycles are cool in theory, but the notion of actually riding
one terrifies me. I don’t want to be controlling, but if she were to go out
and ride a motorcycle, I’d be sick with worry. What should I do? How can I get
over my worries and fears? Or alternatively, how can I convince my girlfriend
to not purchase a motorcycle?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Tigger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tigger,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well the scenario is pretty clear here, although I think your final question is
probably a bit inappropriate. I don’t think you will make any real progress on
solving the core of this issue by showing your partner statistics about
motorcycle accidents or fatalities. So I would say rule out your last question
about changing their mind, I think it will be more productive for you to try
and change the way you think. In general, I think it is far easier to change
one’s own mind than it is to change the minds of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do you get over your own worries and fears? Probably easier said than
done. For motorcycling in particular it might be helpful to ride one yourself.
I’m not suggesting you go out and buy a Ducati and zoom around on the highway.
Instead, I would propose looking for and signing up for a beginners class. This
way, you will learn about how motorcyclists approach riding and maybe you’ll
gain an appreciation for efforts they put into being as safe as possible on the
road. Hopefully, this first-hand experience will help with your fears about
your partner riding her motorcycle. Now this solution isn’t going to be
practical for every worry and fear you have. So I think you also need to
engage in some self-reflection and look inward to understand the root cause of
your worries and fears. You may want to consider some meditation or even some
therapy. Ultimately, I think you also need to separate yourself from your
partner, whether this is in the literal sense of breaking up (which may be
necessary if you can’t handle your different approaches to risk), or it might
be more metaphorical in the sense of separating your individual decisions and
autonomy in your mind. The risks your partner chooses to take, and those you
choose not to take are part of what make each of you who you are. It might
be worth reflecting on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;name-games&quot;&gt;Name Games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I just moved into a new apartment in a new town where I don’t know very many
people. So you can imagine my delight when I ran into a neighbor of mine and
we introduced ourselves and made some small talk. Now while I am sure we did
introduce each other, I cannot remember this person’s name! Cue awkward
encounters in the hallway now as I have to lamely say ‘Hey’ without being able
to make my greeting personal. As a result, I don’t feel confident in asking
this person to hang out with me and I don’t think we’ll ever become friends.
It would be so nice to have a friend in the building and we seemed to really
hit if off when we first stopped and spoke to each other. What can I do to
fix this situation and make a new friend?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Nameless&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nameless,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like it could be a fairly common problem people have, especially
in these kind of casual situations. I think names aside you’ve set yourself a
very ambitious goal in befriending a neighbor. Don’t get me wrong, when you
click with someone and become friends, that can go very well, and it definitely
can happen for neighbors. But I would also say that many people are not going
around looking to become friends with their neighbors. Especially in an
apartment setting, my assumption when I meet people is that they would prefer
having an acquaintance-level of a relationship with their neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hesitations about making friends with neighbors aside, let’s dive into the
name bit of this question. My suggestion is that you just be honest. The next
time you encounter this person in the hallway and you both stop to chat, just
admit that you forgot their name and ask them to remind you. I personally can
be really bad at remembering names, so I often lead with ‘I’m really bad at
remembering names’ and then ask the person to remind me. It is probably also
helpful to offer your name again just in-case they’ve forgotten yours and are
also a bit shy to ask! I’ve found that when I am asking someone to remind me
of their name, I usually provide mine first, this way they are “off the hook”
in the event they’d forgotten mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on January 5, 2022.</summary></entry></feed>