<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-31T16:23:46-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jayaram Hariharan</title><subtitle>Jayaram Hariharan's personal website.</subtitle><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><entry><title type="html">2021-12-30</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-30" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021-12-30" /><published>2021-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-30">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on December 30, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mapping-stuff&quot;&gt;Mapping Stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Some people make really neat maps with all sorts of cool animations. Any
idea how they do this? I’d like to do some magical mapping of my own!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Cartographically Challenged&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cartographically Challenged,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a super interesting question and one I’ve asked myself a lot as I have
seen so many cool cartographic images, animations, and products over the last
few years. So I don’t have all the answers to this question, but I can clue
you in on what I do know about the various software and procedures I’ve seen
people use to generate cool looking maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common software used for making maps is going to be one of the GIS
or Geographical Information System software tools. The industry leaders in this
space are the popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esri.com/en-us/home&quot;&gt;ESRI&lt;/a&gt; ArcMap and ArcGIS
products, although in recent years the open-source
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.qgis.org/en/site/&quot;&gt;QGIS&lt;/a&gt; project has been closing this gap and
provides what I think is a really nice interface. Ultimately, I think your
choice in GIS tool will be dictated by the end-goal of your map making
activities. If you have access to ESRI products and are looking to land a job
in the map making world, then it is worth the time to learn how to use the Arc
products. For hobby map making, I don’t think the license is worth the cost,
however, and you should definitely explore QGIS. Even if
you want a job in GIS, I would say don’t pay for ESRI, the QGIS option is very
similar, and for many things better than the ESRI alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also several programmatic options for generating maps. Both Python
and JavaScript have a number of libraries designed for making maps, so if you
are keen on getting in to making maps via programming, consider checking those
languages and their ecosystems out. There is also
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.generic-mapping-tools.org/&quot;&gt;Generic Mapping Tools&lt;/a&gt;, or GMT, a
favorite of Earth, Ocean, and Planetary scientists that is essentially run from
the command line, although wrapper libraries for Matlab, Julia, and Python
do exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also seen very cool maps generated using
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blender.org/&quot;&gt;Blender&lt;/a&gt;, which is an open-source 3D computer
graphics software. Blender is capable of rendering high quality animations and
other graphics, although there’s a bit of a learning curve and it can be
computationally demanding to generate a graphic using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Map Making,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;computational-methods-for-studying-river-deltas&quot;&gt;Computational Methods for Studying River Deltas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am on the precipice of beginning a research journey looking at the
evolution of river deltas. I’m hoping to do some numerical modeling, remote
sensing, and overall just would like to become familiar with popular numerical
methods for doing this type of work. Where should I start?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-Really Real Person&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RRP,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feels like a question I would write in to myself (if I did that sort
of thing). So I will answer this in a very self-serving way, but that being
said, I encourage you to explore a bit, read the literature, and find the
models and methods best suited to what you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to simulate river delta evolution I encourage you to check out our
&lt;a href=&quot;https://deltarcm.org/pyDeltaRCM/&quot;&gt;pyDeltaRCM&lt;/a&gt; project. This model takes a
simplified approach to modeling the physics behind the formation of a river
delta, and is highly configurable. To analyze model outputs we’re in the
midst of developing a companion package, currently named
&lt;a href=&quot;https://deltarcm.org/DeltaMetrics/&quot;&gt;DeltaMetrics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, on the other hand, you want to analyze some remote sensing data, you might
consider checking out &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonschwenk.github.io/RivGraph/&quot;&gt;RivGraph&lt;/a&gt;.
RivGraph lets you analyze channel networks through the lens of graph theory,
and comes packaged with a bunch of built-in tools and methods for easy
quantitative analysis of your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Python" /><category term="Programming" /><category term="Earth Science" /><category term="River Deltas" /><category term="Cartography" /><summary type="html">Advice given on December 30, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2021-12-22</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-22" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021-12-22" /><published>2021-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-22">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on December 22, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tis-already-the-season&quot;&gt;‘tis already the season?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I can’t believe 2021 is already winding down. I’ve really lost track of time
this year, and now I find myself in a difficult situation. It is less than a
week from Christmas and I’ve yet to purchase any gifts for my loved ones!
What should I do? How can I possibly get them all gifts in such a short time?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Holi-dazed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holi-dazed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve done it this time eh? Just kidding! It is a bit of a sticky situation,
but fear-not, for I have a few ideas. This year in particular makes late gift
buying a bit challenging as supply chain issues due to the pandemic have caused
inventory shortages in-stores and delayed deliveries of packages ordered
online. If you have the time, the simplest solution might be to take a day and
visit a mall or outdoor shopping center where there are just a bunch of stores
and shop until you are able to find something for every person on your list.
If you’re a bit more pressed for time, then I think you need to explore more
out-of-the-box ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the critical aspects of gift purchasing for a group of people with
different interests within a short time frame is to select something generic
enough that it can be purchased for most if not all members of the group, and
to pick something that is non-physical. Meaning the gift should not be
something you need to physically obtain or make; we live in a digital
age, so purchasing a digital gift should be possible. To that end, my
controversial solution to this problem is to leverage a new and controversial
technology: the blockchain. Now I know this is an incredibly unpopular idea
in some circles, but I think for this particular scenario the comical maxim:
&lt;em&gt;“Bitcoin fixes this,”&lt;/em&gt; may actually be appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I fully flesh out this idea, I would like to take you, my dear reader,
back a few decades. Once upon a time, it was not unheard of for children to be
gifted physical stock shares or bond certificates on special occasions. Often,
these were gifts from an elder family member or friend, with the intention of
fostering good saving and investing habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the tail-end of 2021, the vast majority of the population is aware of the
existence of Bitcoin and blockchain technology, even if they do not have a
personal stake in this technology themselves. While there is no doubt the
entire cryptocurrency space is rife with speculation, participation in crypto
by financial institutions lends some credence to the notion that crypto is
here to stay in some shape or form. Therefore, this is the perfect time to gift
members of your family a small chunk of cryptocurrency! This gift represents
an opportunity for them to have some involvement in this new burgeoning
financial system; after all, nobody wants to be left behind. From the practical
gift-giving vantage point, gifting crypto is relatively fast as it happens
digitally. You can opt to informally give less tech-savvy gift recipients an
“IOU” of sorts and hold their crypto for them, while you can create a
“paper wallet” (quickly and for free) for the techie members of your
family (or offer to send them their gifts directly if they already hold
crypto). Given the wide variety of cryptocurrencies available at this time,
you can customize the gift to suit each individual. For the traditionalist in
the family you could gift them a more established coin such as Bitcoin or
Ethereum. Sports fans or artists could receive an NFT. While environmentalists
might be interested in the newer, greener, projects such as Algorand which aim
to be carbon-neutral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a new technology, this gift will flip the older stock/bond gifting model on
its head as this does not promote traditional methods of saving and
investing, but instead offers each recipient a chance to dip their toes into
the wild west that is the cryptocurrency landscape. More importantly, this
gift is non-physical, and can be procured faster than a regular physical
present, making it a feasible option for one who is tight on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Holidays,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;traveling-aspirations&quot;&gt;Traveling Aspirations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am in a relationship with a wonderful person, but we have a problem we
can’t seem to figure out: we’re both terrible planners. I tend to get stressed
out by the overwhelming possibilities, and she tends to wait too long before
making plans. And we’re both fairly preoccupied with work-related things, so we
don’t mull things over well. The result is that we desperately need a vacation
but can’t seem to pick anything because no one really wants to do the planning
legwork. How can we make progress on this and finally get out of town?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-Stuck at home&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stuck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well as far as relationship problems go, this seems to be a pretty tame one,
so congratulations to you and your partner. Besides adopting some sort of
strict timeline for planning a trip and assigning tasks (which does not sound
fun), I think I have some interesting alternative ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a quick, spur of the moment weekend-getaway, the trip could be planned on
Friday night itself. Just pull up a map and find a local bed and breakfast
within a few hours drive, call them up to make a reservation for the next day,
and drive over Saturday morning. Sometimes a quick and simple trip with no
planning can be an enjoyable experience; it also gets you out of your regular
routine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re seeking a trip further away for a longer time, I think your best bet
is to go through a travel agency of some kind. Don’t stress! You don’t
actually need to think about all of the possible destinations, there are a
number of companies that offer a &lt;strong&gt;surprise&lt;/strong&gt; destination package. I believe
the gist of these packages is that you outline your dates of travel, budget,
and interests. Then the agency mails you a package containing the plane tickets
and a full itinerary for your trip. No planning required on your end! The
downside to this strategy is that I’m sure there is a premium you have to pay
to get someone else to plan your trip, but in exchange you will be spared what
sounds like a considerable amount of time and stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good vacation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on December 22, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2021-12-17</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-17" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021-12-17" /><published>2021-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-17">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on December 17, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;popular-party-goer&quot;&gt;Popular Party-Goer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I find myself in a quandary. I’ve been invited to two birthday
parties for two different friends on the same night. Both events
are dinners, and are scheduled at virtually the same time, so it
is impossible for me to attend both. How do I decide which to
attend? Can I manage this without letting the other friend down?
While these two people are not close friends themselves, they
follow each other on social media and will see my picture at whichever
event I choose to attend. I feel trapped between a rock and a hard
place; are there any good options here?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-Popular Person&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Popular Person,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess this is a fortunate problem to have? I can say I’ve never
experienced this myself. However I do think you have several options
in this scenario. You can choose one party to attend and tell the other
friend what you are going to be doing, then the social media post about the
event will not surprise the friend whose party you skip. Alternatively, and
this might be the option I would choose, you could skip both events, avoiding
the awkward social media pictures and subsequent fallout, and also giving
yourself a quiet night in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry that this is all I’ve been able to come up with, maybe I wasn’t the best
advice columnist to approach with this particular question. If this is
unsatisfactory, maybe try asking Amy or Jeeves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html">Advice given on December 17, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2021-12-07</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-07" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021-12-07" /><published>2021-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-07">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on December 7, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-they-remind-me&quot;&gt;How They Remind Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have been a closet Nickelback fan for years at this point. Why can’t
everyone admit that they are an awesome band and we were wrong as a society
to dislike them? Anyway, my issue is that all of my friends will casually talk
trash about Nickelback whenever one of their songs is on, and skip to the next
song when possible. I’ve kept my mouth shut so far but I am losing my patience,
they are a good band! How can I admit to my friends that I like Nickelback? Can
I convince them to enjoy the music too? Will they make fun of me? Help!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-Nickelbacker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nickelbacker,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hm, this is quite the quandary. I’ve never totally understood the societal
dislike for Nickelback myself, although I’m not a die-hard fan either.
You’ve posed two slightly different questions: how to admit to your friends
that you like Nickelback, and how to convince them to like the band too. I
definitely think you should feel comfortable doing the former. True friends
may tease you a bit for your unconventional taste in music, but they will
still be your friends. I’m not sure you will be able to convince them to like
the music, however. It sounds like they are familiar enough with Nickelback to
skip songs when they come on, so it sounds like your friends have a clear idea
of who Nickelback is and what their music sounds like. So I’d probably let go
of this notion that you’ll be able to turn them into fans, but definitely let
your friends know that you enjoy the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;streaming-science&quot;&gt;Streaming Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As you may or may not be aware, the American Geophysical Union’s Fall Meeting
is rapidly approaching. In our brave new world, this meeting has a hybrid
twist, and is requiring all talks be pre-recorded. While recording my
presentation an idea occurred to me - could I stream myself working and doing
science on Twitch or YouTube? Is there a market for this kind of thing?
Is this a good idea? Can I become big sci-nfluencer? So that’s my idea, to
stream myself writing some code, making some figures, and writing manuscripts.
What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-Sci-nfluencer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sci-nfluencer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool idea! I say go for it. If you find the prospect of streaming yourself to
be too intimidating, I would recommend at the very least uploading any talks
that you have recorded to YouTube or a similar platform. This way folks who
are interested in your work will have a chance to see the awesome things you do
and the crystal clear presentations you are able to give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the only way to know if there is a market and viewers for this type of
thing is by trying it out, I do like your ideas of streaming specific tasks.
As a potential viewer, I would be interested in seeing how someone else makes
their figures, or their process for putting together presentations. If I have
some writing to do, maybe it would be motivating to write alongside a
streaming-personality such as yourself. I think graphics in particular could be
appealing to people, things like how to make a cool map or plot might entice
people by showing them both &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to make nice graphics, but also &lt;em&gt;how long&lt;/em&gt;
the process takes when you are familiar with the workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a neat idea so I definitely think you should give it a try. I don’t know
the first thing about streaming so I can’t recommend a particular platform, but
I think you’ve identified the two market leaders with Twitch and Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best of luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Interpersonal Relationships" /><category term="Self-Confidence" /><summary type="html">Advice given on December 7, 2021.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2021-12-01</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-01" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2021-12-01" /><published>2021-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2021-12-01">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on December 1, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gandalf-the-graying&quot;&gt;Gandalf the Graying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m a fairly young guy and I’ve just noticed my first gray hair!
This is freaking me out! I’m losing my confidence and need some advice
on how to remain positive, confident, and feel good about myself as I
age.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Gandalf the Graying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandalf,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally understand, but don’t stress (you’ll gray even faster).
Aging isn’t necessarily a negative thing, gray hairs may be seen by
some as a sign of experience. Maintain a positive attitude, it will keep
you young at heart and a pleasant person to be around. If these measures
do not work, you can always explore dying your hair. There are many
hair color products out there, I would just encourage you to test a
little bit of the product on your skin first to make sure you do not have
an allergic reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay positive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;greasy-fingers&quot;&gt;Greasy Fingers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have recently begun conducting maintenance on my bicycle. This has
been great except for all of the grease! How can I get this bloody stuff
off of my hands? Have any advice for me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-Greasy Fingers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Greasy Fingers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand your dilemma and have some suggestions. I am not an expert on
hand washing, however I believe the fact that the grease is oily makes it
difficult to wash off of your hands. One potential solution is to prevent
grease from ever getting on your hands in the first place. This is pretty
simple to achieve, just wear some gloves whenever you do maintenance on
your bike. If, however, you do end up with grease on your hands, there are
soap products specifically designed for this purpose. These soaps typically
have some sort of particulate matter or grid in them which helps get the
oily grease off of your hands. Alternatively, I believe if you wash
multiple times and use old hand towels to help remove the grease, the
towel replaces the grit in specialty soaps. Just remember that the grease
will end up on your hand towel, so it is important to use an old towel
if you’re going to use this strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best of luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Aging" /><category term="Personal Hygiene" /><summary type="html">Advice given on December 1, 2021.</summary></entry></feed>