<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-03T15:47:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jayaram Hariharan</title><subtitle>Jayaram Hariharan's personal website.</subtitle><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><entry><title type="html">2022-07-03</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-07-03" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-07-03" /><published>2022-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-07-03">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on July 3, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workplace-whistler&quot;&gt;Workplace Whistler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The person in the office next to me whistles loudly in the morning.
It’s joyful whistling, and I don’t want to take that away from them,
but it drives me up a wall. How can I delicately ask them to stop?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Whistleblower&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whistleblower,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sympathize with your situation and agree that it is a difficult position to
be in. It sounds like your objective is pretty clear, you want them to stop.
In this case, I guess you can’t tune them out or listen to other music and
actually want some quiet while you work. If you have a cordial relationship
with this coworker, I suggest you approach them directly. It is best to be
upfront and honest, but as you say, you also have to be delicate. When you
speak with your coworker about this, I think you should make this a problem
you are having, rather than their problem. You don’t want to say they are
too loud, you should say that you are sensitive to noise, and need quiet to
work efficiently. If you phrase it in a non-accusatory way, and frame the
solution as a problem you have, not something they are doing wrong, I think
this will not create a rift between you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on July 3, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-06-16</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-16" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-16" /><published>2022-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-16">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 16, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;crushed-by-crypto&quot;&gt;Crushed by Crypto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Well anyone who has read the news lately knows that the entire cryptocurrency
market has crashed. As someone who was late to the game, but invested a lot
of money into cryptocurrencies, I am feeling crushed. How can I feel better
about myself? I’ve lost a lot of self-confidence and self-esteem as I feel
I made such poor decisions with my money. What should I do?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Crushed by Crypto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crushed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel for you and I hope you don’t feel too down in the dumps. As you seem to
be aware, you aren’t the only one losing out now, the entire crypto sector is
experiencing a selloff and stocks have also been taking a plunge. I understand
that you feel a bit less confident, but you need to view this event in a more
positive light and try to make the most of it. Take it as a learning experience,
and start learning about economics and markets so that the next time you make
risky investments you are better educated. As far as feeling better about
yourself, I think some time will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sick-of-the-sell&quot;&gt;Sick of the Sell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a friend who is a great person, but they have a problem. They’re very
charismatic and always “selling” people on whatever thing they have recently
picked up. For a stranger, this interaction seems great - they walk away
having learned about something new to check out. As a friend, I’m tired of
being given a sales pitch whenever I ask my friend how they are doing or what
is new in their life. How can tell me friend to stop trying to “sell” me on
things?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sick&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting dilemma. It sounds like you may be the less chatty of the
two of you, if your friend enjoys talking with strangers about their latest
find. To your question, I think it is a bit of a tricky spot to be in. I don’t
know your specific relationship with this friend, but if you tell them to stop
“selling” you on things, you run the risk that they will just not tell you
about what is new in their life. That situation might be the beginning of the
end for your friendship. It might be better to approach this with a more open
mind, and listen to your friend, but tell them that you have different tastes,
likes, and dislikes. Maybe you can ask them to recommend things to you that
they think are things &lt;em&gt;you specifically&lt;/em&gt; will like, and trust your friend to
be understanding. If you choose to have this kind of conversation, I would be
careful to put the “problem” on yourself, rather than on your friend. The
issue shouldn’t be presented as your friend “selling” you on stuff, but should
be presented as &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; feeling overwhelmed or uncomfortable with trying so many
new things, or doing things outside of your comfort zone. By focusing this
conversation on yourself rather than projecting the issue onto your friend, I
think you’ll have a better chance of getting the results you want without
losing your friendship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Personal Finance" /><category term="Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 16, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-06-10</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-10" /><published>2022-06-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-10">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 10, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;candy-crusher&quot;&gt;Candy Crusher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a sweet tooth, and it’s becoming a problem. I’ve always had a love of
sweets, but things are beginning to spiral out of control. I generally am
enjoying candy bars or other sweets more frequently than I eat regular food.
I find myself getting irritated, tired, and sad when I go too long without
eating some candy. I need to break this habit. Do you have any suggestions
for me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Candy Crusher&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crusher,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to solving any behavioral issue (in my opinion) is admitting and
recognizing that the problem exists. You’ve clearly done this and I applaud
you for it. Next, you must develop a reasonable and achievable plan of action
to change your behavior. Do you keep all of your candy in a single place? Maybe
you can start there and place some healthy snacks in front of the candy to
encourage you to make healthier decisions. You could try logging your daily
candy intake, and setting goals based on your current consumption. Once you are
able to get some sort of realistic plan put together, I suggest you go ahead
and try to follow it. Be prepared to have backslides and moments of weakness,
that’s totally normal! But I’m proud of you for recognizing your bad habit and
trying to fix it. The journey will be difficult, but you’ll ultimately
feel healthier and better in the long-run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dramady&quot;&gt;Dramady&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve developed this nasty habit of comically over-reacting to things that
happen to me. For example, if I’m misstep and slightly stumble while walking,
I will exaggerate the stumble and sometimes roll on the ground. I don’t act
injured, but I turn awkward physical situations into comically over-acted
performances. While this is funny, and seems fine sometimes, I’ve started
doing this &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the time. I need some help breaking this habit. How can I
accomplish that?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Drama King&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;King,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You sound like a funny guy. It sounds like what was a funny one-off gag has now
become an almost compulsive habit. In that case, I’d agree that things are a
bit out of control. Do you over-act when you are totally alone and there is
nobody there to watch your “performance”? In any case, I think you need to be
hyper-aware of your actions for a little while. It might even help for you to
intentionally stumble, or misstep, and then &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; act out. This might help
re-train your brain and muscle-memory to stop over-acting when these situations
crop up more naturally. If you’re unable to fix this behavior yourself, you
could consult some sort of therapist or other healthcare professional to help
you break this habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Acting" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 10, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-06-01</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-01" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-01" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-01">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 1, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coworker-competition&quot;&gt;Coworker Competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We have an exercise competition at work based on tracking the amount of time
people work out. Our company is global, so the various offices compete with
each other. These competitions are generally evaluated on a month-by-month
basis where for each month, your office is competing with another one to 
exercise more. My problem is a pretty straightforward one, my office keeps
losing! At first I wasn’t bothered, because I figured it is just a casual
office contest, and we’ll win some and lose some over the course of a few
months. But this hasn’t happened. Instead, we just keep losing over and over.
The competitions have been going on for 6 months and our record is 0-6. Is 
there a way I can (politely) get my coworkers motivated to compete and to win
in this inter-office competition?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Competitive Colleague&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well now, at least you’re willing to admit you are competitive. It’s clear that
you must be much more competitive than most folks at your office. I think it’s
going to be tough to go around and get your colleagues to exercise more for the
purposes of winning these little inter-office contests. Most people will see 
them as fun competitions, but nothing to really think about or care too deeply
about. I think for you, it’d be a better use of your competitive drive to find
another environment within which you can go out and win. You should check and
see if your city has intramural sports leagues, there you may be able to find
a set of teammates that cares much more about winning. On the office side, 
maybe you can reach out to the organizer of these competitions to see if they
can also create an individual leaderboard across all offices. That way you’d 
be able to compete as hard as you want, without being frustrated with the
performance of your office as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mid-day-gym-day&quot;&gt;Mid-Day-Gym-Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve found a gym near my office that I really enjoy working out at. I’ve also
learned that it is least crowded mid-day, and I’m lucky enough to have a job
where I can duck out for an hour in the middle of the afternoon to get a 
workout in. Do you think I have to shower at the gym before returning to the
office? It can be such a hassle, but I suspect it would be poor form on my
part to hang out at my desk for a few hours all sweaty. Let me know what you
think, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sweaty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweaty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what the right answer is here. You’ve got to shower before returning
to the office. It’s both unprofessional and simply rude to your coworkers
and colleagues who have to share the office-space with you. Take the extra 5
or 10 minutes and shower after your workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><category term="Exercise" /><category term="Personal Hygiene" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 1, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-05-23</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-05-23" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-05-23" /><published>2022-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-05-23">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on May 23, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coworker-confusion&quot;&gt;Coworker Confusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve got a workplace situation I’m hoping you can help me with. I’ve been at
my latest job for about a month, and I’m having trouble befriending one of
my coworkers. We don’t work directly together, but we do sit in the same
room, along with a number of other people. At first, I thought he just didn’t
like me, but I’ve found I get along with everyone else in our office. I’ve
been trying to be as friendly as I can be by offering to grab lunch, trying
to chat when we happen to be at the water cooler together, and inviting him
to join me and our other co-workers when we get together after work. He is
never outright rude to me, but his answers are usually pretty curt, and our
conversations, as a result, are very short. Do you have any advice for me?
I am not sure if this guy doesn’t like me, or if he’s just not very sociable.
What should I do? How can I get this co-worker of mine to open up and be
my friend?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Confounded Colleague&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confounded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You sound like you have such good intentions, I’m sorry you haven’t been able
to befriend this coworker of yours. It sounds like you’ve done some
self-reflection to see if you are the problem. Since you’re friends with many
of your other coworkers, I agree that you are probably not someone incapable
of making friends. It could be that this coworker of yours just doesn’t want
to make any friends in the office. Maybe they are thinking about work when you
try to chat with them at the water cooler, and so their mind isn’t on your
conversation and they give you short replies. I think there are a million
possible reasons this person isn’t warming up to you. The real question I have
for you, is why does this bother you so much? It sounds like you’ve got a
group of your colleagues that you hang out with and are friends with. I’d
suggest you leave this guy alone, and let him do his own thing, and you can
talk to and hang out with your friends. You’ve made it clear you are willing
to be friendly with him, so he should have gotten the hint that you’re happy to
talk to or spend time with him if he so chooses. I think you have done all you
can do, and now it is up to your coworker to decide to engage in this
friendship if he wants one. Don’t stress about it, not everyone gets along as
fast friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relax!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;colleague-crush&quot;&gt;Colleague Crush&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So we had a new person join my company a few months ago, and he’s such a
great guy. I didn’t mean to, but I totally have a crush on him, and I’ve
tried to drop him hints by timing my coffee breaks to line up with his, and
joining him for lunch outside. The problem is, he doesn’t seem to have a
clue! I don’t want to do anything inappropriate or create an awkward
situation at work, so what should I do now? Can I confess my true feelings
for this guy?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Crushin’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crushin’,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like you’re in a bit of a pickle for sure. I think you know what I’m
going to tell you, but it just isn’t what you want to hear. The best thing
you can do for your career, and to maintain your workplace environment, is to
drop it and stop pursuing this guy, no matter how careful you have been so far.
For all you know, you may be putting this guy in a very awkward position. He
might not be as clueless as you think, but doesn’t know how to politely reject
your advances and is instead trying to ignore them. If you can’t drop this, I
think you can certainly tell him how you feel. But if you go down that route
I think you should just be direct, and find a way to have that conversation
that isn’t awkward, regardless of what his answer is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><category term="Romance" /><summary type="html">Advice given on May 23, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-18</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-18" /><published>2022-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-18">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 18, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-scream&quot;&gt;I scream&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I see that you reside in Austin, TX. Very cool. I’m coming to visit Austin,
and wanted to get your suggestions for ice cream places to check out. From
what I can tell by looking at the weather forecasts it’s already gotten
quite warm over there, and I’m looking to stay cool and enjoy some ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I Scream For Ice Cream&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screamer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, this is a pretty &lt;em&gt;chill&lt;/em&gt; question indeed. The “best” ice cream in town is
obviously a matter of opinion, and to be honest, I’ve yet to identify my
personal favorite. However, I can name my current top 3 picks, which are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilikelick.com/&quot;&gt;Lick&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amysicecreams.com/&quot;&gt;Amy’s&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://jenis.com/&quot;&gt;Jeni’s&lt;/a&gt;. Of the three, I believe both Lick and Amy’s were
founded in Austin, while Jeni’s was started in Ohio. All worth checking out in
my humble opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay cool,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eating-on-the-run&quot;&gt;Eating on the Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So I’ve been starting to run farther distances than I used to, and I am
starting to get hungry on my runs. Do you think it’s weird to take a snack
and munch as I jog? What should I take to eat and drink on my runs? Any
thoughts or suggestions are appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Joggin’ and gobblin’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Jogger,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting question. I can’t speak to what will work for you, but
I can tell you what my strategy for re-fueling mid-run used to be. I used to
plan to eat and drink for runs that were going to take longer than 1 hour.
Anything less than an hour I decided was short enough that I could wait until
the run was over to re-hydrate and eat. When I was going to eat on a run, I
think I tried to time it out so that I was having a bite and a sip of water
roughly every half an hour. This way I never had to eat or drink too much at
a time, and was also getting a more consistent supply of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d read online that because you lose a fair amount of salt when you sweat, it
can be good to drink something other than pure water. To be frugal, I used to
just add a little bit of salt to my water bottle to help replenish the salt I
was sweating out. You could also surely get powdered mixes, or sports drinks to
have during your jog. Food-wise, I used to eat raisins as they are high in
sugar, inexpensive, and will keep you energized. I could also imagine some
nuts would be tasty while running. There are, of course, the “goo” products
often sold to endurance athletes which are designed to provide the fuel you
need to continue your activity, although they are certainly more costly than
the simple raisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck out there,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Exercise" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 18, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-12</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-12" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-12" /><published>2022-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-12">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 12, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-cookin&quot;&gt;What’s Cookin’?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I feel like I am eating out too often. I want to cook more at home, but
have trouble finding the time and the motivation. Even when I have the time
and want to cook, I often don’t know what to make. Any advice? I realize
eating out all the time probably isn’t the healthiest for my wallet or
for my health. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Chef-to-be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chef-to-be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, it sounds like you want to make some smart moves and I commend you for
that. I feel like this is something I’ve heard from various people over the
course of my life, and so hopefully that makes you feel better about this
issue you’re having. Step one to changing any undesired behavior is
acknowledging it and deciding you actually want to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how to change can pose it’s own set of challenges. You’ve pointed out
that it is likely healthier for you to cook your own meals, and is financially
a better move too. Remember to keep that in mind to help motivate yourself
to cook. It can also help to have some recipes you enjoy eating to motivate
yourself to make those meals. I suggest you try keeping your kitchen stocked
with fresh groceries, so that when you look in your fridge or pantry you see
ingredients you find appealing and can cook into tasty meals. Having the right
foods already at home may help you want to cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think choosing what to make is an incredibly personal decision. It also comes
down to your individual skill in the kitchen, available ingredients,
kitchenware, and the amount of time you have to prepare a given meal. Given
these constraints, it might help you to start looking up various lists of
recipes, maybe group them by prep time. This way, you can quickly consult your
curated list when it is time to cook, and you won’t waste cooking time looking
up a recipe to make. If you do your research, this list of recipes may also
help guide your shopping at the grocery store, to ensure you always have some
of the common items you need to make your favorite dishes. You’ll also be able
to make a quick dish when pressed for time, or get involved in a longer cooking
process when you have the time to spare. I wish you the best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay hungry,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Cooking" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 12, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-05</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-05" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-05" /><published>2022-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-05">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 5, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;becoming-an-expert&quot;&gt;Becoming an Expert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time trying to be as environmentally friendly as possible.
For example I don’t just toss things into recycling, I wash them out, and
sort them by the material type. I maintain a compost pile to allow natural
material to compost. I even take timed (short) showers every other day to
conserve water. At what point (if any) am I an environmental expert?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Green&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like you’re quite green indeed! Interesting question, makes me want to
know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you want to be an “expert” at all. Does it matter how other people
perceive your environmental credentials? Are you looking to obtain a job or
pivot to a role that is in the environmental space? If your goal is at all
related to your profession, then I suspect there will be limits to how far
your environmental actions in your personal life can take you. Generally for
professional advancement it is more advantageous to either have educational
credentials in the field, or have on-the-job experience, which you could obtain
at any level within the target industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job-stuff aside, if you simply want to brag to your friends and family about
how environmental you are, then I suppose this question is a bit simpler. The
idea of being an “expert” is a bit vague and hard to pin down, as you’ve
realized. Especially for something like being “environmentally-friendly,” as
our understanding of the environment and climate is steadily evolving. There is
the popular “10,000 hours makes you an expert” line of thinking, which I
believe was proposed by Malcolm Gladwell. So maybe you should estimate the
hours you dedicate to your environmental behaviors, and once they tally up to
about 10,000 hours, you can just start calling yourself an environmental
expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay clean,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flexin&quot;&gt;Flexin’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;To be candid, things have been going pretty well for me recently. After a
few years of regular exercise, I am feeling pretty fit and trim. I have
just moved into a new job that is much more rewarding in all aspects, which
is also making me happier. However I realize that right now, as well as for
the past few years, things have not been going so well for many people. So,
in a sense I think I feel a bit guilty about my successes and my happiness.
How can I enjoy my life without this guilt? I don’t try to go around rubbing
my happiness in other peoples’ faces, but sometimes I feel like I am just
flexing unnecessarily when I talk about how well work is going, or how
great I feel after a workout. Have any advice for me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Flexosaurus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flexosaurus,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow you sound like such a nice person! It is truly very considerate of you to
keep other peoples’ experiences in your thoughts even as things are going so
well for you. Unless you are walking around boasting about your life, I don’t
think you really have anything to worry about, and it doesn’t sound like you
do much bragging. If you feel like you are in a good place, and have the
time to spare, it might be fulfilling for you to volunteer in your community.
When you volunteer, you can contribute to bringing happiness into the lives
of people in your community who may not currently be in as privileged a
position as you are. Even if you want to volunteer and help clean up a park, an
activity that does not require direct interaction with others, as you pick up
litter you may think to yourself that some person will visit the park later
and have a better experience because they didn’t have to look at trash. So my
advice is simple, just try to be proactive and give back if you are feeling
guilty about your happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Environment" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Success" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 5, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-03-20</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-20" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-03-20" /><published>2022-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-20">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on March 20, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;freezer-burn&quot;&gt;Freezer Burn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I opened up my freezer to a bunch of food with freezer burn on it. Do you know its still safe to eat? How can I prevent this from happening in the future? Sorry for such a basic question, but this is where I find myself today.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Burnt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnt,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello. Freezer burn is less than ideal for sure, but at least you should feel
some relief when you learn that the food should still be safe to consume. My
understanding of freezer burn is that it is simply what happens when frozen
food begins to thaw, and moisture begins to escape the food and re-freezes on
its exterior. For this reason, freezer burn changes the texture of the food
(usually negatively), but does not indicate that the food has spoiled. However,
if you had a power outage and food totally thawed and re-froze, it is possible
things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; spoil when you lost power. So just be careful / aware of how the
freezer burn came about. Typically, I’ve found my items in the freezer can end
up with some freezer burn after they’ve sat in the freezer for a long time,
in these cases I assume the opening and closing of the door over time caused
moisture to escape and re-freeze, or is introduced from outside to create the
freezer burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay frosty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gaps-between-classes&quot;&gt;Gaps Between Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am in my first year of college and am having trouble making the most of my time in between classes. I have some gaps between different lectures of varying lengths, sometimes I have an hour, sometimes I have three, but I struggle with what I should be doing during these free periods. In high school I never had this type of free time in the middle of the day besides my lunch period. What do you recommend I do? Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Gap for Kids&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gap,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair question, it is an interesting situation you may find yourself in for the
rest of your collegiate career. There are a number of different things people
do with their mid-day gaps, some of which I am sure you may be familiar with,
but others that may be novel to you. Some ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare for your next class by reviewing or reading ahead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you live close by, go back home and eat or do some housework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Swing by the gym and get a workout in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find an on-campus job and schedule shifts during your longer breaks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a position as a lab assistant - some tasks like washing dishes in a wet lab don’t require close supervision so you can likely do that when you have free time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join a club and become involved in it’s running, some may have offices and administrative tasks that need to be taken care of during the day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit the library and read a book&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eat some lunch or a snack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the weather is good, find a nice spot to take a nap outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the weather is bad, there may be designated nap spots on campus (I don’t know if this is actually true)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take your pick, some of those suggestions are certainly better than others.
But different things work for different people, so just try to figure out what
works best for you. Best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="School" /><summary type="html">Advice given on March 20, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-03-11</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-11" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-03-11" /><published>2022-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-11">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on March 11, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gracefully-taking-a-compliment&quot;&gt;Gracefully Taking A Compliment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I was wondering if you could give me some advice on how to gracefully accept
compliments. I am lucky enough to be surrounded by such kind people, but I
feel so awkward when someone gives me a compliment. I tend to freeze up a bit
and say something like “thank you, you’re too kind”. But this feels so
strange, so any suggestions you have on how I could improve the way I receive
compliments would be much appreciated. To clarify, I am talking about
work-related compliments along the lines of “great work on X” or “this
report was really useful,” as opposed to those related to my style or taste
in movies (both of which I have no problems accepting compliments about).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Grace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grace,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is such a nice situation to be in. Clearly you are not so awkward about
receiving compliments that people have decided to stop complimenting you on
your work! Humbly, I will say I personally don’t receive a ton of compliments,
but I think I can still offer you some advice. It sounds like you are a bit
bashful about the compliments, maybe because you feel they are undeserved or
too much for the effort or work you put in. I think the first step to getting
around this awkwardness is understanding that people do not compliment you
out of obligation; compliments are almost always voluntary and genuinely
meant. If someone is giving you a compliment, even if it is for something
small to you, it may mean something more to them. Once you internalize this
fact, it may be easier to understand the value you are providing to your
coworkers, and subsequently it may be easier to accept their compliments.
The one thing you should not do in this kind of a work setting is downplay the
work and say something like “oh thanks, it was nothing”. Then your coworkers
might start to take your effort and work for granted. I think a short and
simple, “thank you, I’m glad you found it helpful” or similar is the best way
to respectfully acknowledge this type of a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the great question,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sorry-machine&quot;&gt;Sorry Machine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I think I am a serial apologizer. I find myself constantly saying “sorry” or
apologizing for minor inconveniences, or sometimes apologizing for things
that are neither inconveniences nor in my control to begin with. Last week it
rained and I caught myself apologizing to someone for the weather! As if
I could do anything about that! How can I stop being such a sorry machine?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Apologizer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologizer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is good to be apologetic in some situations, but I agree with you, it is
certainly possible to apologize too much. This is a bit of an unfortunate
habit you’ve gotten yourself into. I think this habit, like any other, is a
bit difficult to break. Step one might be slowing down the pace at which you
speak and taking a pause to think before you say something. Maybe you’ve
avoided the all-too-common “likes,” “ums,” and other filler words with your
“sorrys” and other apologies. Generally, I think the easiest way to break any
speaking habit is to speak more slowly and carefully consider your words before
you say them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Manners" /><summary type="html">Advice given on March 11, 2022.</summary></entry></feed>