<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-01T14:06:06-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jayaram Hariharan</title><subtitle>Jayaram Hariharan's personal website.</subtitle><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><entry><title type="html">2022-06-01</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-01" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-01" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-01">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 1, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coworker-competition&quot;&gt;Coworker Competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We have an exercise competition at work based on tracking the amount of time
people work out. Our company is global, so the various offices compete with
each other. These competitions are generally evaluated on a month-by-month
basis where for each month, your office is competing with another one to 
exercise more. My problem is a pretty straightforward one, my office keeps
losing! At first I wasn’t bothered, because I figured it is just a casual
office contest, and we’ll win some and lose some over the course of a few
months. But this hasn’t happened. Instead, we just keep losing over and over.
The competitions have been going on for 6 months and our record is 0-6. Is 
there a way I can (politely) get my coworkers motivated to compete and to win
in this inter-office competition?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Competitive Colleague&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well now, at least you’re willing to admit you are competitive. It’s clear that
you must be much more competitive than most folks at your office. I think it’s
going to be tough to go around and get your colleagues to exercise more for the
purposes of winning these little inter-office contests. Most people will see 
them as fun competitions, but nothing to really think about or care too deeply
about. I think for you, it’d be a better use of your competitive drive to find
another environment within which you can go out and win. You should check and
see if your city has intramural sports leagues, there you may be able to find
a set of teammates that cares much more about winning. On the office side, 
maybe you can reach out to the organizer of these competitions to see if they
can also create an individual leaderboard across all offices. That way you’d 
be able to compete as hard as you want, without being frustrated with the
performance of your office as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mid-day-gym-day&quot;&gt;Mid-Day-Gym-Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve found a gym near my office that I really enjoy working out at. I’ve also
learned that it is least crowded mid-day, and I’m lucky enough to have a job
where I can duck out for an hour in the middle of the afternoon to get a 
workout in. Do you think I have to shower at the gym before returning to the
office? It can be such a hassle, but I suspect it would be poor form on my
part to hang out at my desk for a few hours all sweaty. Let me know what you
think, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sweaty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweaty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what the right answer is here. You’ve got to shower before returning
to the office. It’s both unprofessional and simply rude to your coworkers
and colleagues who have to share the office-space with you. Take the extra 5
or 10 minutes and shower after your workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><category term="Exercise" /><category term="Personal Hygiene" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 1, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-05-23</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-05-23" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-05-23" /><published>2022-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-05-23">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on May 23, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coworker-confusion&quot;&gt;Coworker Confusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve got a workplace situation I’m hoping you can help me with. I’ve been at
my latest job for about a month, and I’m having trouble befriending one of
my coworkers. We don’t work directly together, but we do sit in the same
room, along with a number of other people. At first, I thought he just didn’t
like me, but I’ve found I get along with everyone else in our office. I’ve
been trying to be as friendly as I can be by offering to grab lunch, trying
to chat when we happen to be at the water cooler together, and inviting him
to join me and our other co-workers when we get together after work. He is
never outright rude to me, but his answers are usually pretty curt, and our
conversations, as a result, are very short. Do you have any advice for me?
I am not sure if this guy doesn’t like me, or if he’s just not very sociable.
What should I do? How can I get this co-worker of mine to open up and be
my friend?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Confounded Colleague&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confounded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You sound like you have such good intentions, I’m sorry you haven’t been able
to befriend this coworker of yours. It sounds like you’ve done some
self-reflection to see if you are the problem. Since you’re friends with many
of your other coworkers, I agree that you are probably not someone incapable
of making friends. It could be that this coworker of yours just doesn’t want
to make any friends in the office. Maybe they are thinking about work when you
try to chat with them at the water cooler, and so their mind isn’t on your
conversation and they give you short replies. I think there are a million
possible reasons this person isn’t warming up to you. The real question I have
for you, is why does this bother you so much? It sounds like you’ve got a
group of your colleagues that you hang out with and are friends with. I’d
suggest you leave this guy alone, and let him do his own thing, and you can
talk to and hang out with your friends. You’ve made it clear you are willing
to be friendly with him, so he should have gotten the hint that you’re happy to
talk to or spend time with him if he so chooses. I think you have done all you
can do, and now it is up to your coworker to decide to engage in this
friendship if he wants one. Don’t stress about it, not everyone gets along as
fast friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relax!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;colleague-crush&quot;&gt;Colleague Crush&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So we had a new person join my company a few months ago, and he’s such a
great guy. I didn’t mean to, but I totally have a crush on him, and I’ve
tried to drop him hints by timing my coffee breaks to line up with his, and
joining him for lunch outside. The problem is, he doesn’t seem to have a
clue! I don’t want to do anything inappropriate or create an awkward
situation at work, so what should I do now? Can I confess my true feelings
for this guy?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Crushin’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crushin’,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like you’re in a bit of a pickle for sure. I think you know what I’m
going to tell you, but it just isn’t what you want to hear. The best thing
you can do for your career, and to maintain your workplace environment, is to
drop it and stop pursuing this guy, no matter how careful you have been so far.
For all you know, you may be putting this guy in a very awkward position. He
might not be as clueless as you think, but doesn’t know how to politely reject
your advances and is instead trying to ignore them. If you can’t drop this, I
think you can certainly tell him how you feel. But if you go down that route
I think you should just be direct, and find a way to have that conversation
that isn’t awkward, regardless of what his answer is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><category term="Romance" /><summary type="html">Advice given on May 23, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-18</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-18" /><published>2022-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-18">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 18, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-scream&quot;&gt;I scream&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I see that you reside in Austin, TX. Very cool. I’m coming to visit Austin,
and wanted to get your suggestions for ice cream places to check out. From
what I can tell by looking at the weather forecasts it’s already gotten
quite warm over there, and I’m looking to stay cool and enjoy some ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I Scream For Ice Cream&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screamer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, this is a pretty &lt;em&gt;chill&lt;/em&gt; question indeed. The “best” ice cream in town is
obviously a matter of opinion, and to be honest, I’ve yet to identify my
personal favorite. However, I can name my current top 3 picks, which are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilikelick.com/&quot;&gt;Lick&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amysicecreams.com/&quot;&gt;Amy’s&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://jenis.com/&quot;&gt;Jeni’s&lt;/a&gt;. Of the three, I believe both Lick and Amy’s were
founded in Austin, while Jeni’s was started in Ohio. All worth checking out in
my humble opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay cool,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eating-on-the-run&quot;&gt;Eating on the Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So I’ve been starting to run farther distances than I used to, and I am
starting to get hungry on my runs. Do you think it’s weird to take a snack
and munch as I jog? What should I take to eat and drink on my runs? Any
thoughts or suggestions are appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Joggin’ and gobblin’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Jogger,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting question. I can’t speak to what will work for you, but
I can tell you what my strategy for re-fueling mid-run used to be. I used to
plan to eat and drink for runs that were going to take longer than 1 hour.
Anything less than an hour I decided was short enough that I could wait until
the run was over to re-hydrate and eat. When I was going to eat on a run, I
think I tried to time it out so that I was having a bite and a sip of water
roughly every half an hour. This way I never had to eat or drink too much at
a time, and was also getting a more consistent supply of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d read online that because you lose a fair amount of salt when you sweat, it
can be good to drink something other than pure water. To be frugal, I used to
just add a little bit of salt to my water bottle to help replenish the salt I
was sweating out. You could also surely get powdered mixes, or sports drinks to
have during your jog. Food-wise, I used to eat raisins as they are high in
sugar, inexpensive, and will keep you energized. I could also imagine some
nuts would be tasty while running. There are, of course, the “goo” products
often sold to endurance athletes which are designed to provide the fuel you
need to continue your activity, although they are certainly more costly than
the simple raisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck out there,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Exercise" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 18, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-12</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-12" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-12" /><published>2022-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-12">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 12, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-cookin&quot;&gt;What’s Cookin’?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I feel like I am eating out too often. I want to cook more at home, but
have trouble finding the time and the motivation. Even when I have the time
and want to cook, I often don’t know what to make. Any advice? I realize
eating out all the time probably isn’t the healthiest for my wallet or
for my health. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Chef-to-be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chef-to-be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, it sounds like you want to make some smart moves and I commend you for
that. I feel like this is something I’ve heard from various people over the
course of my life, and so hopefully that makes you feel better about this
issue you’re having. Step one to changing any undesired behavior is
acknowledging it and deciding you actually want to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how to change can pose it’s own set of challenges. You’ve pointed out
that it is likely healthier for you to cook your own meals, and is financially
a better move too. Remember to keep that in mind to help motivate yourself
to cook. It can also help to have some recipes you enjoy eating to motivate
yourself to make those meals. I suggest you try keeping your kitchen stocked
with fresh groceries, so that when you look in your fridge or pantry you see
ingredients you find appealing and can cook into tasty meals. Having the right
foods already at home may help you want to cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think choosing what to make is an incredibly personal decision. It also comes
down to your individual skill in the kitchen, available ingredients,
kitchenware, and the amount of time you have to prepare a given meal. Given
these constraints, it might help you to start looking up various lists of
recipes, maybe group them by prep time. This way, you can quickly consult your
curated list when it is time to cook, and you won’t waste cooking time looking
up a recipe to make. If you do your research, this list of recipes may also
help guide your shopping at the grocery store, to ensure you always have some
of the common items you need to make your favorite dishes. You’ll also be able
to make a quick dish when pressed for time, or get involved in a longer cooking
process when you have the time to spare. I wish you the best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay hungry,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Cooking" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 12, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-05</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-05" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-05" /><published>2022-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-05">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 5, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;becoming-an-expert&quot;&gt;Becoming an Expert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time trying to be as environmentally friendly as possible.
For example I don’t just toss things into recycling, I wash them out, and
sort them by the material type. I maintain a compost pile to allow natural
material to compost. I even take timed (short) showers every other day to
conserve water. At what point (if any) am I an environmental expert?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Green&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like you’re quite green indeed! Interesting question, makes me want to
know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you want to be an “expert” at all. Does it matter how other people
perceive your environmental credentials? Are you looking to obtain a job or
pivot to a role that is in the environmental space? If your goal is at all
related to your profession, then I suspect there will be limits to how far
your environmental actions in your personal life can take you. Generally for
professional advancement it is more advantageous to either have educational
credentials in the field, or have on-the-job experience, which you could obtain
at any level within the target industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job-stuff aside, if you simply want to brag to your friends and family about
how environmental you are, then I suppose this question is a bit simpler. The
idea of being an “expert” is a bit vague and hard to pin down, as you’ve
realized. Especially for something like being “environmentally-friendly,” as
our understanding of the environment and climate is steadily evolving. There is
the popular “10,000 hours makes you an expert” line of thinking, which I
believe was proposed by Malcolm Gladwell. So maybe you should estimate the
hours you dedicate to your environmental behaviors, and once they tally up to
about 10,000 hours, you can just start calling yourself an environmental
expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay clean,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flexin&quot;&gt;Flexin’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;To be candid, things have been going pretty well for me recently. After a
few years of regular exercise, I am feeling pretty fit and trim. I have
just moved into a new job that is much more rewarding in all aspects, which
is also making me happier. However I realize that right now, as well as for
the past few years, things have not been going so well for many people. So,
in a sense I think I feel a bit guilty about my successes and my happiness.
How can I enjoy my life without this guilt? I don’t try to go around rubbing
my happiness in other peoples’ faces, but sometimes I feel like I am just
flexing unnecessarily when I talk about how well work is going, or how
great I feel after a workout. Have any advice for me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Flexosaurus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flexosaurus,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow you sound like such a nice person! It is truly very considerate of you to
keep other peoples’ experiences in your thoughts even as things are going so
well for you. Unless you are walking around boasting about your life, I don’t
think you really have anything to worry about, and it doesn’t sound like you
do much bragging. If you feel like you are in a good place, and have the
time to spare, it might be fulfilling for you to volunteer in your community.
When you volunteer, you can contribute to bringing happiness into the lives
of people in your community who may not currently be in as privileged a
position as you are. Even if you want to volunteer and help clean up a park, an
activity that does not require direct interaction with others, as you pick up
litter you may think to yourself that some person will visit the park later
and have a better experience because they didn’t have to look at trash. So my
advice is simple, just try to be proactive and give back if you are feeling
guilty about your happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Environment" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Success" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 5, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-03-20</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-20" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-03-20" /><published>2022-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-20">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on March 20, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;freezer-burn&quot;&gt;Freezer Burn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I opened up my freezer to a bunch of food with freezer burn on it. Do you know its still safe to eat? How can I prevent this from happening in the future? Sorry for such a basic question, but this is where I find myself today.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Burnt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnt,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello. Freezer burn is less than ideal for sure, but at least you should feel
some relief when you learn that the food should still be safe to consume. My
understanding of freezer burn is that it is simply what happens when frozen
food begins to thaw, and moisture begins to escape the food and re-freezes on
its exterior. For this reason, freezer burn changes the texture of the food
(usually negatively), but does not indicate that the food has spoiled. However,
if you had a power outage and food totally thawed and re-froze, it is possible
things &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; spoil when you lost power. So just be careful / aware of how the
freezer burn came about. Typically, I’ve found my items in the freezer can end
up with some freezer burn after they’ve sat in the freezer for a long time,
in these cases I assume the opening and closing of the door over time caused
moisture to escape and re-freeze, or is introduced from outside to create the
freezer burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay frosty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gaps-between-classes&quot;&gt;Gaps Between Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am in my first year of college and am having trouble making the most of my time in between classes. I have some gaps between different lectures of varying lengths, sometimes I have an hour, sometimes I have three, but I struggle with what I should be doing during these free periods. In high school I never had this type of free time in the middle of the day besides my lunch period. What do you recommend I do? Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Gap for Kids&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gap,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fair question, it is an interesting situation you may find yourself in for the
rest of your collegiate career. There are a number of different things people
do with their mid-day gaps, some of which I am sure you may be familiar with,
but others that may be novel to you. Some ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare for your next class by reviewing or reading ahead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you live close by, go back home and eat or do some housework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Swing by the gym and get a workout in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find an on-campus job and schedule shifts during your longer breaks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a position as a lab assistant - some tasks like washing dishes in a wet lab don’t require close supervision so you can likely do that when you have free time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join a club and become involved in it’s running, some may have offices and administrative tasks that need to be taken care of during the day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit the library and read a book&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eat some lunch or a snack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the weather is good, find a nice spot to take a nap outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the weather is bad, there may be designated nap spots on campus (I don’t know if this is actually true)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take your pick, some of those suggestions are certainly better than others.
But different things work for different people, so just try to figure out what
works best for you. Best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="School" /><summary type="html">Advice given on March 20, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-03-11</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-11" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-03-11" /><published>2022-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-03-11">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on March 11, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gracefully-taking-a-compliment&quot;&gt;Gracefully Taking A Compliment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I was wondering if you could give me some advice on how to gracefully accept
compliments. I am lucky enough to be surrounded by such kind people, but I
feel so awkward when someone gives me a compliment. I tend to freeze up a bit
and say something like “thank you, you’re too kind”. But this feels so
strange, so any suggestions you have on how I could improve the way I receive
compliments would be much appreciated. To clarify, I am talking about
work-related compliments along the lines of “great work on X” or “this
report was really useful,” as opposed to those related to my style or taste
in movies (both of which I have no problems accepting compliments about).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Grace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grace,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is such a nice situation to be in. Clearly you are not so awkward about
receiving compliments that people have decided to stop complimenting you on
your work! Humbly, I will say I personally don’t receive a ton of compliments,
but I think I can still offer you some advice. It sounds like you are a bit
bashful about the compliments, maybe because you feel they are undeserved or
too much for the effort or work you put in. I think the first step to getting
around this awkwardness is understanding that people do not compliment you
out of obligation; compliments are almost always voluntary and genuinely
meant. If someone is giving you a compliment, even if it is for something
small to you, it may mean something more to them. Once you internalize this
fact, it may be easier to understand the value you are providing to your
coworkers, and subsequently it may be easier to accept their compliments.
The one thing you should not do in this kind of a work setting is downplay the
work and say something like “oh thanks, it was nothing”. Then your coworkers
might start to take your effort and work for granted. I think a short and
simple, “thank you, I’m glad you found it helpful” or similar is the best way
to respectfully acknowledge this type of a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the great question,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sorry-machine&quot;&gt;Sorry Machine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I think I am a serial apologizer. I find myself constantly saying “sorry” or
apologizing for minor inconveniences, or sometimes apologizing for things
that are neither inconveniences nor in my control to begin with. Last week it
rained and I caught myself apologizing to someone for the weather! As if
I could do anything about that! How can I stop being such a sorry machine?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Apologizer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologizer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is good to be apologetic in some situations, but I agree with you, it is
certainly possible to apologize too much. This is a bit of an unfortunate
habit you’ve gotten yourself into. I think this habit, like any other, is a
bit difficult to break. Step one might be slowing down the pace at which you
speak and taking a pause to think before you say something. Maybe you’ve
avoided the all-too-common “likes,” “ums,” and other filler words with your
“sorrys” and other apologies. Generally, I think the easiest way to break any
speaking habit is to speak more slowly and carefully consider your words before
you say them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Manners" /><summary type="html">Advice given on March 11, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-02-28</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-28" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-02-28" /><published>2022-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-28">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on February 28, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harsh-words-make-me-sad&quot;&gt;Harsh Words Make Me Sad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a problem at work, but I’m not sure if it is a “me” problem, or a
larger problem with the workplace culture. When my manager criticizes my
work, I feel really sad. Fortunately, I know I am not the only one who’s
work gets critiqued - I believe this type of criticism is leveled at all of
my co-workers in equal measure. However I don’t get the impression it fazes
them, while I usually need to take a few minutes to re-focus and center
myself before I can continue my day. Am I just too soft? Is this an actual
problem or am I just dramatic? Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shaken Up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaken,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s okay to be sensitive. Without the details it is hard to gauge whether or
not you are too sensitive, however. If your office is a bit larger, try to
get a sense for how other managers provide feedback to their teams. The wording
you provide, “criticism”, and “critique”, are a bit harsher than what I’d
expect, a more positive workplace culture might have you using a word
like “feedback” to describe the comments you get about your work from a
manager. If you are comfortable confiding in any of your immediate coworkers,
you might want to ask them if they ever feel your manager’s comments are too
harsh. Their answer could let you know if your feelings are shared by others,
or if indeed you are overly sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My admittedly harsh take, is that this is likely a good growing and learning
experience for you. You’ve gotten stuck in an uncomfortable situation, and it
is smart of you to be trying to sort this out. Whether or not your fellow
co-workers think your manager is too hard on y’all is almost unimportant; how
you, as an individual, handle it is what matters most. You are unlikely to get
your supervisor to change their ways, and it doesn’t seem like a productive use
of time to try. It is more practical for you to either change your state of
mind and accept that they are a bit more harsh than you’d like, or start
figuring out how to remove yourself from the situation. I am assuming that your
manager is otherwise a good colleague and coworker, and really this is the only
sticking point you have with them. So given those ideas, you should weigh your
options and think about your job, your career, and your life in a bigger
picture sense, to determine what the best course of action for you in this
situation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;afraid-to-fall&quot;&gt;Afraid to Fall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve recently had a few health scares and am a bit wary of many physical
activities now. My doctors all say I can get back to life as usual, but I
feel like I have a mental block, and I can’t get over my fears. Do you have
any suggestions to help me get back to living an exciting and active life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,
Nervous Nellie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Nellie,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I can’t pretend to know the details of your exact situation, I can’t help
but think that your reaction is totally normal. If you haven’t already brought
up this mental challenge you’re facing to your doctors, I’d suggest you do that
first, as I am not a medical professional. They may have some good suggestions,
or may be able to refer you to a therapist or psychiatrist that can help you
get over your mental hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think you’ve had enough of doctors’ offices, I guess my suggestion would
be to take things one day at a time. While you will have to push yourself a
little bit outside of your comfort zone to get back to what you used to do,
don’t be upset if progress is slow and incremental. These things take time, and
you certainly don’t want to create a new physical or mental problem for
yourself. So just take things slow, and progress at your own rate, and know
that what you are feeling is totally understandable, I think most people would
be hesitant to resume activities that were previously perilous to them!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Criticism" /><category term="Courage" /><summary type="html">Advice given on February 28, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-02-10</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-02-10" /><published>2022-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-10">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on February 10, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unsolicited-advice-on-graduate-school&quot;&gt;Unsolicited Advice on Graduate School&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello folks, this week I am departing from the usual advice column to provide
some (partially) unsolicited advice on graduate school.
I am going to attempt to distill the advice I seem to give on a semi-annual
basis to strangers and acquaintances who are choosing a graduate program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to break this into 3 parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should you go to graduate school?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to identify potential schools, programs, and advisors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What to keep in mind while in school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-should-you-go-to-graduate-school&quot;&gt;1. Should you go to graduate school?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this is an incredibly personal decision, and many personal factors
may enhance or limit your ability to attend graduate school in the first place.
Independent of those factors, I think it is necessary to identify &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you
want to go to graduate school. There are many reasons, but you need to be sure
that you find a compelling one. If you cannot find a strong reason to go, you
are likely to struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to keep in mind when making this decision are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are my current opportunities in the workforce? Is school more
attractive than any of these options?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is my financial situation? Graduate school is rarely a time during
which you will be able to accumulate wealth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What opportunities do I wish to have in the future? Can graduate school
help unlock these, or would I be better off finding a job that provides me
with relevant work experience for my dream career?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I feel about doing homework and taking exams? These are largely
unavoidable when you go to school.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Am I willing to spend significant amounts of time reading and writing? No
matter the field of study, you will likely spend large amounts of time
both reading and writing as most graduate degrees culminate in a thesis
or dissertation (and maybe some research publications along the way).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-how-to-identify-potential-schools-programs-and-advisors&quot;&gt;2. How to identify potential schools, programs, and advisors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have decided to go to graduate school, the next decision is to
identify specific schools and programs to apply to. Then, depending on which
you are accepted to, you have to decide which to attend. So what makes for a
good fit between a prospective student and a particular research group?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventional advice is to search for a program in which you feel accepted. A
place where you feel welcomed by the faculty and other graduate students, as
these people will be your professors and peers for a number of years. This
is certainly great advice! It is typically accompanied by the (obvious)
suggestion that the group you join should be doing research you are
interested in, and would like to conduct. All of this advice is totally sound,
but I think there are additional elements many people forget to consider (at
least I did), which are worth thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first has to do with the school itself, what is its reputation? Where is
it? While these factors can be relatively unimportant if the specific program
you are applying to is incredibly well known at the institution, having an
understanding of how the rest of the world and country perceive the institution
is important. If you end up job searching outside of your field, the prestige
of the university will supersede the reputation of your graduate program. The
location of the university may impact where graduates tend to work; some
schools have well established reputations and pipelines to jobs at regional
companies and agencies. If you know what type of career you plan to pursue
after school, then you should see whether the school you are considering has
many alumni in those type of roles at the specific companies or institutions
you would like to one day work at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second, has to do with the specific graduate program, and basically
involves the same question. What is its reputation in the field? Most
university departments are quite broad relative to individual lab research
sub-disciplines and specialties. It is important to ensure the program you
attend has some expertise in the sub-field you are interested in.
To get a feel for this, you should browse the department’s
website and visit individual faculty pages to see what their research focus is
in. This way you can see if your research interests align broadly with the
research the department is conducting. The prestige of the department or
program itself is important to consider if you are looking to work in the field
after graduating. You might be surprised to learn about the relatively small or
unknown schools across the globe which are highly regarded in your field. To
gauge that type of prestige, I suggest you look up some manuscripts in your
desired field of study, and look through the references to find the labs or
institutions which appear frequently. This is one indicator of how established
an individual department is in the field. Another method of identifying these
programs is to talk to someone you know, preferably someone not in academia,
about the field to try and learn whether or not there are a handful of programs
you should definitely be considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third, and final consideration is arguably the most important, and that is
the selection of a research group and advisor. Now do not forget, this is
definitely a 2-way street, as prospective students search for a good fit with
a lab, advisors search for their newest advisee. As a prospective student, you
should search for a lab which does research that you are interested in, this
is something you cannot really be flexible on. This step should greatly shrink
the number of potential research groups within your broader scientific field.
Standard advice from here is to suggest you get in touch with the PI of the
lab, try to speak with them and see if you are likely to get along, and then
try to speak with some current students to understand what the student
experience in the lab group and in the graduate program is like. Beyond these
steps, which are incredibly important, I think there are a few further
considerations worth making. How long do students typically stay in this
group? Another way of putting that is: how long is the typical degree for a
member of this group? What do students of this research group tend to go do
after they graduate? What skills do students of this group obtain and leave
with? Is there an expectation to publish, if so, how successful are students
in publishing? Is the group highly collaborative with other researchers within
or external to the university? Are students involved in these collaborations?
I think most of these questions can be posed to current graduate students when
you speak with them about joining the group. However, I also think you should
do some of this investigation for yourself, as each individual is going to
present you with a biased version of what they experienced. To do this, you
might examine the research group website (if there is one) to try and see
how long students seem to be there, and what alumni of the group end up doing.
Fortunately for you, senior graduate students are likely searching for jobs
themselves, and I think that it is increasingly common for them to have some
sort of web-presence, where you may be able to see their C.V. or learn more
about their graduate experience. I think this type of investigation on the
part of the prospective student can be very beneficial, as this will help you
understand what experiences or opportunities may be available, and what skills
you will exit the group having. To understand the publishing habits of the
group, I would look up the PI on Google Scholar. This should give you an
indication of how frequent they publish, who common collaborators are,
and roughly what the expectations for publishing are for students of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-what-to-keep-in-mind-while-in-school&quot;&gt;3. What to keep in mind while in school&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in school your primary focus should be on completing the objectives
required to complete your degree requirements and graduate. However, I would
caution against having a myopic focus on these objectives, as the requirements
for obtaining a degree may not directly align with the qualifications
necessary to begin your dream career. The alignment of graduate program
requirements with job requirements will vary based on your field, as well as
your target career. Even so, I think all students should keep these cautionary
words in the back of their minds. Students who wish to become professors in the
future, for example, should not lose track of the facets of professorship
beyond research, such as teaching, and proposal writing. These prospective
professors should do what they can to gain experience teaching, designing
course curricula, and writing proposals as much as they can while graduate
students, to improve the quality of their future academic applications. That is
just one example, for students eyeing careers in industry, it is worth looking
up job advertisements to understand the skills employers are looking for. These
may or may not match the skills you are developing as a student, and some may
be technical skills you can learn in courses, or incorporate into some aspect
of your graduate work. I’d encourage future and current students to take the
time to make this evaluation at least semi-annually if not on a quarterly
basis so that there is time to make small adjustments and find opportunities
while in school that can ultimately increase the quality of your future job
applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember that your graduate school experience comes down to what you
are able to get out of it. Nobody can care about or prioritize your experience
more than you can. I went to a talk about graduate school once where the
professor giving the lecture reminded everyone that they are just a single
student of many in their supervisor’s lab group - and as such, you must be
your own best advocate. It doesn’t matter how supportive or well-meaning your
professors and peers are, the onus is on the individual to get what they need
to get done, even if it means pestering people when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this rambling piece of advice is able to help at least 1 person
better navigate their graduate school experience. The standard advice column
will be back next time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Unsolicited" /><category term="Graduate School" /><summary type="html">Advice given on February 10, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-02-04</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-04" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-02-04" /><published>2022-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-02-04">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on February 4, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-the-will-to-exercise&quot;&gt;Finding the Will to Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;While it is winter, I can’t help but think ahead to the summer. When I do so,
I realize I’m not in the physical shape I wish I was in. While I don’t know you
personally, I get the impression you are reasonably fit and stay in shape.
So that being said, I’m hoping you can give me some advice on how to motivate
myself to exercise. If it helps any, I am hoping to run more, as I would like
to spend more time outside. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Bugs Runny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs Runny,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well one option is to imagine someone is hunting you down like a rabbit! But
maybe I can try to provide some more realistic advice as well. Personally, I
have found that identifying an end goal or objective for an activity can help
me find the motivation needed to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to run a marathon, it is helpful to find a training
plan, and stick to it, to increase your chances of success. You’ve vaguely
mentioned wanting to be in some sort of physical shape, but I would encourage
you to more specifically define the end goal. Once you’ve done that, you can
break up the overall objective into smaller milestones, and chart yourself a
realistic path to achieving each one of them. If you are aiming for a target
weight on the scale, maybe define your ultimate goal, and then set intermediate
targets. This gives you the opportunity to track your progress, and adjust the
overall timeline if you find you are unable to drop the pounds at the rate
you wanted to. This is normal! If you cannot hit the targets you set, it is not
indicative of failure to act or improve yourself, it may just mean you’ve set
unrealistic or unachievable timelines for your goals. So I wouldn’t get
discouraged if you miss a self-identified milestone, if it happens multiple
times, I would just step back and maybe re-adjust your overall timeline to
match what is physically feasible for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the daily or weekly level, you need to think about how your actions and
decisions will impact your future self. If we think about being in shape by
the summertime, that may sound like it is far away as it is only February now.
But, how long does it take to get into shape? If you aren’t actively trying to
improve your physical fitness, maybe you’ll even slide further from being in
shape between now and the summer. The decision to go on a run today is a small
but incremental step in the direction you want to head. So just remember to
keep the overall time horizons in perspective, and think about future you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;re-oat-milk&quot;&gt;Re: Oat Milk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hi Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I saw your advice last week regarding oat milk. I agree that Oatly is pretty
good. As someone who has been on a lactose-free diet for a long time, I just
wanted to also point your reader to soy milk as a potential alternative.
In particular, I have gotten used to the Silk brand of soy milk and would
recommend that to your reader. Silk has been making alternative milks for a
while, and I would suggest trying their almond and oat milks as well as the
soy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for the tip! Hopefully last week’s advice seeker sees this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Motivation" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Well-Being" /><summary type="html">Advice given on February 4, 2022.</summary></entry></feed>