<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-18T16:41:37-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jayaram Hariharan</title><subtitle>Jayaram Hariharan's personal website.</subtitle><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><entry><title type="html">2022-08-18</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-08-18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-08-18" /><published>2022-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-08-18">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on August 18, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wrong-side-of-the-bed&quot;&gt;Wrong Side of the Bed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I had an unfortunate experience recently. I woke up one morning with a
stiff neck, and it hurt a bit to turn my head to the left. This is unusual,
but not entirely unprecedented, so I wasn’t worried, and figured this
feeling would go away by the end of the day. To my dismay, this was not the
case. Instead, I suffered a sore neck for the next few days. This physical
malady represented, for me, a clear and distressing sign of my own aging and
mortality. It sounds ridiculous, but this experience threw me into a bit of
a funk for a few days. I’m hoping you have some advice that I can use to
help age more gracefully. Let me know!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Your Newest Middle-Aged Reader&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reader,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, this is a tough one to answer, as the solution to your negative thoughts
is a bit of a personal challenge you need to overcome. Each person deals with
their mortality and aging differently. One thing to keep in mind is that there
is really nothing you can do about aging. Time moves in one direction, and you
will get older, there’s nothing you can do about that part of the equation.
You can, however, try to stay physically fit and limber, and maintain a
positive mindset. So I’d recommend getting regular exercise and stretching if
you aren’t already doing that, and following a healthy diet. My favorite song
about the aging process is Baz Luhrmann’s
“&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sTJ7AzBIJoI&quot;&gt;Everybody’s Free (To Wear Sunscreen)&lt;/a&gt;”, the
spoken word adaptation of Mary Schmich’s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chicagotribune.com/columns/chi-schmich-sunscreen-column-column.html&quot;&gt;column&lt;/a&gt;
in the Chicago Tribune. So to quote Mary and Baz: “If I could offer you only
one tip for the future, sunscreen would be it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Aging" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Health" /><summary type="html">Advice given on August 18, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-08-06</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-08-06" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-08-06" /><published>2022-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-08-06">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on August 6, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;decision-making-difficulties&quot;&gt;Decision Making Difficulties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I struggle with making decisions, both big and small. For example, I have
difficulty choosing an ice cream flavor when I’m at the store. I also have
trouble with decisions like where to go on vacation. I’m looking for some
help to become more decisive. Do you have any ideas or strategies you
think could help me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Undecided Advice-Seeker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undecided,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you aren’t the only person with this issue. Beyond simply telling you
to be more decisive, I have an unconventional suggestion. There is a pretty
strange book called “The Dice Man” written by George Cockcroft under the
pseudonym Luke Rhinehart, the protagonist of the story. I don’t think that the
book itself is all that great, however the main premise is related to your
dilemma. Luke believes his life is too boring, and seeks to add some
randomness. To do this, he rolls a dice before every decision. He creates a
number of different possible actions, and associates them with a single number
or a set of numbers on the die. He then rolls the die, and takes the action
associated with the number he rolled. You could adopt this approach to help
you make decisions when you are having trouble deciding between two or more
different options. It is a bit of a strange process, but it might help take the
difficulty out of making hard decisions. Maybe over time you’d realize you do
have a preference for certain choices in various scenarios!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Courage" /><category term="Success" /><summary type="html">Advice given on August 6, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-07-25</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-07-25" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-07-25" /><published>2022-07-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-07-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-07-25">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on July 25, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sigh-guy&quot;&gt;Sigh Guy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One of my colleagues at work is what I’ve defined as a “sigh guy”. He is a
good worker, but he always seems so uneager to actually do any work. When
we have a meeting and he is assigned a task, or when someone stops by his
desk to ask a question, he begins with an audible sigh. Then he gets on with
the work, or starts to answer the question. How can I tell him this sigh is
very off-putting? It makes me feel like I am burdening him by asking him to
do his job? To be fair, I don’t know if he is actually burdened, or if this
is some sort of physical habit he associated with getting his brain in gear
before performing a task. What should I do?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Congenial Coworker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congenial,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting situation to be in. It doesn’t sound like your coworker is actually
complaining about his role. Like you admit, you don’t know if these sighs are
because he is reluctant to work, or just a habit. That being said, I don’t
think you can or should ask him to stop. It sounds like he’s a good worker,
and you didn’t indicate that his answers to questions are rude or
condescending. So if that is the case, let the guy sigh. I think you should
reframe your mindset to be more accommodating of different people’s habits and
quirks. Sure, maybe sighing has a bit of a negative connotation in the
workplace, but it doesn’t seem like it is indicative of anything particularly
bad in this case. If this guy is a trainee of yours, you could mention this if
you are involved in his professional development. But if you are a colleague,
and not in a mentorship role, I would stay out of it and not mention the
sighing at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on July 25, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-07-03</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-07-03" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-07-03" /><published>2022-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-07-03">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on July 3, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workplace-whistler&quot;&gt;Workplace Whistler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The person in the office next to me whistles loudly in the morning.
It’s joyful whistling, and I don’t want to take that away from them,
but it drives me up a wall. How can I delicately ask them to stop?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Whistleblower&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whistleblower,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sympathize with your situation and agree that it is a difficult position to
be in. It sounds like your objective is pretty clear, you want them to stop.
In this case, I guess you can’t tune them out or listen to other music and
actually want some quiet while you work. If you have a cordial relationship
with this coworker, I suggest you approach them directly. It is best to be
upfront and honest, but as you say, you also have to be delicate. When you
speak with your coworker about this, I think you should make this a problem
you are having, rather than their problem. You don’t want to say they are
too loud, you should say that you are sensitive to noise, and need quiet to
work efficiently. If you phrase it in a non-accusatory way, and frame the
solution as a problem you have, not something they are doing wrong, I think
this will not create a rift between you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on July 3, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-06-16</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-16" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-16" /><published>2022-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-16">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 16, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;crushed-by-crypto&quot;&gt;Crushed by Crypto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Well anyone who has read the news lately knows that the entire cryptocurrency
market has crashed. As someone who was late to the game, but invested a lot
of money into cryptocurrencies, I am feeling crushed. How can I feel better
about myself? I’ve lost a lot of self-confidence and self-esteem as I feel
I made such poor decisions with my money. What should I do?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Crushed by Crypto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crushed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel for you and I hope you don’t feel too down in the dumps. As you seem to
be aware, you aren’t the only one losing out now, the entire crypto sector is
experiencing a selloff and stocks have also been taking a plunge. I understand
that you feel a bit less confident, but you need to view this event in a more
positive light and try to make the most of it. Take it as a learning experience,
and start learning about economics and markets so that the next time you make
risky investments you are better educated. As far as feeling better about
yourself, I think some time will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sick-of-the-sell&quot;&gt;Sick of the Sell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a friend who is a great person, but they have a problem. They’re very
charismatic and always “selling” people on whatever thing they have recently
picked up. For a stranger, this interaction seems great - they walk away
having learned about something new to check out. As a friend, I’m tired of
being given a sales pitch whenever I ask my friend how they are doing or what
is new in their life. How can tell me friend to stop trying to “sell” me on
things?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sick&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sick,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting dilemma. It sounds like you may be the less chatty of the
two of you, if your friend enjoys talking with strangers about their latest
find. To your question, I think it is a bit of a tricky spot to be in. I don’t
know your specific relationship with this friend, but if you tell them to stop
“selling” you on things, you run the risk that they will just not tell you
about what is new in their life. That situation might be the beginning of the
end for your friendship. It might be better to approach this with a more open
mind, and listen to your friend, but tell them that you have different tastes,
likes, and dislikes. Maybe you can ask them to recommend things to you that
they think are things &lt;em&gt;you specifically&lt;/em&gt; will like, and trust your friend to
be understanding. If you choose to have this kind of conversation, I would be
careful to put the “problem” on yourself, rather than on your friend. The
issue shouldn’t be presented as your friend “selling” you on stuff, but should
be presented as &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; feeling overwhelmed or uncomfortable with trying so many
new things, or doing things outside of your comfort zone. By focusing this
conversation on yourself rather than projecting the issue onto your friend, I
think you’ll have a better chance of getting the results you want without
losing your friendship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Personal Finance" /><category term="Relationships" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 16, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-06-10</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-10" /><published>2022-06-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-10">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 10, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;candy-crusher&quot;&gt;Candy Crusher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a sweet tooth, and it’s becoming a problem. I’ve always had a love of
sweets, but things are beginning to spiral out of control. I generally am
enjoying candy bars or other sweets more frequently than I eat regular food.
I find myself getting irritated, tired, and sad when I go too long without
eating some candy. I need to break this habit. Do you have any suggestions
for me?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thanks,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Candy Crusher&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crusher,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to solving any behavioral issue (in my opinion) is admitting and
recognizing that the problem exists. You’ve clearly done this and I applaud
you for it. Next, you must develop a reasonable and achievable plan of action
to change your behavior. Do you keep all of your candy in a single place? Maybe
you can start there and place some healthy snacks in front of the candy to
encourage you to make healthier decisions. You could try logging your daily
candy intake, and setting goals based on your current consumption. Once you are
able to get some sort of realistic plan put together, I suggest you go ahead
and try to follow it. Be prepared to have backslides and moments of weakness,
that’s totally normal! But I’m proud of you for recognizing your bad habit and
trying to fix it. The journey will be difficult, but you’ll ultimately
feel healthier and better in the long-run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dramady&quot;&gt;Dramady&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve developed this nasty habit of comically over-reacting to things that
happen to me. For example, if I’m misstep and slightly stumble while walking,
I will exaggerate the stumble and sometimes roll on the ground. I don’t act
injured, but I turn awkward physical situations into comically over-acted
performances. While this is funny, and seems fine sometimes, I’ve started
doing this &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the time. I need some help breaking this habit. How can I
accomplish that?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Drama King&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;King,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You sound like a funny guy. It sounds like what was a funny one-off gag has now
become an almost compulsive habit. In that case, I’d agree that things are a
bit out of control. Do you over-act when you are totally alone and there is
nobody there to watch your “performance”? In any case, I think you need to be
hyper-aware of your actions for a little while. It might even help for you to
intentionally stumble, or misstep, and then &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; act out. This might help
re-train your brain and muscle-memory to stop over-acting when these situations
crop up more naturally. If you’re unable to fix this behavior yourself, you
could consult some sort of therapist or other healthcare professional to help
you break this habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Acting" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 10, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-06-01</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-01" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-06-01" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-06-01">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on June 1, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coworker-competition&quot;&gt;Coworker Competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We have an exercise competition at work based on tracking the amount of time
people work out. Our company is global, so the various offices compete with
each other. These competitions are generally evaluated on a month-by-month
basis where for each month, your office is competing with another one to 
exercise more. My problem is a pretty straightforward one, my office keeps
losing! At first I wasn’t bothered, because I figured it is just a casual
office contest, and we’ll win some and lose some over the course of a few
months. But this hasn’t happened. Instead, we just keep losing over and over.
The competitions have been going on for 6 months and our record is 0-6. Is 
there a way I can (politely) get my coworkers motivated to compete and to win
in this inter-office competition?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Competitive Colleague&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitive,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well now, at least you’re willing to admit you are competitive. It’s clear that
you must be much more competitive than most folks at your office. I think it’s
going to be tough to go around and get your colleagues to exercise more for the
purposes of winning these little inter-office contests. Most people will see 
them as fun competitions, but nothing to really think about or care too deeply
about. I think for you, it’d be a better use of your competitive drive to find
another environment within which you can go out and win. You should check and
see if your city has intramural sports leagues, there you may be able to find
a set of teammates that cares much more about winning. On the office side, 
maybe you can reach out to the organizer of these competitions to see if they
can also create an individual leaderboard across all offices. That way you’d 
be able to compete as hard as you want, without being frustrated with the
performance of your office as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mid-day-gym-day&quot;&gt;Mid-Day-Gym-Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve found a gym near my office that I really enjoy working out at. I’ve also
learned that it is least crowded mid-day, and I’m lucky enough to have a job
where I can duck out for an hour in the middle of the afternoon to get a 
workout in. Do you think I have to shower at the gym before returning to the
office? It can be such a hassle, but I suspect it would be poor form on my
part to hang out at my desk for a few hours all sweaty. Let me know what you
think, thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sweaty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweaty,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what the right answer is here. You’ve got to shower before returning
to the office. It’s both unprofessional and simply rude to your coworkers
and colleagues who have to share the office-space with you. Take the extra 5
or 10 minutes and shower after your workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><category term="Exercise" /><category term="Personal Hygiene" /><summary type="html">Advice given on June 1, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-05-23</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-05-23" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-05-23" /><published>2022-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-05-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-05-23">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on May 23, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coworker-confusion&quot;&gt;Coworker Confusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’ve got a workplace situation I’m hoping you can help me with. I’ve been at
my latest job for about a month, and I’m having trouble befriending one of
my coworkers. We don’t work directly together, but we do sit in the same
room, along with a number of other people. At first, I thought he just didn’t
like me, but I’ve found I get along with everyone else in our office. I’ve
been trying to be as friendly as I can be by offering to grab lunch, trying
to chat when we happen to be at the water cooler together, and inviting him
to join me and our other co-workers when we get together after work. He is
never outright rude to me, but his answers are usually pretty curt, and our
conversations, as a result, are very short. Do you have any advice for me?
I am not sure if this guy doesn’t like me, or if he’s just not very sociable.
What should I do? How can I get this co-worker of mine to open up and be
my friend?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Confounded Colleague&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confounded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You sound like you have such good intentions, I’m sorry you haven’t been able
to befriend this coworker of yours. It sounds like you’ve done some
self-reflection to see if you are the problem. Since you’re friends with many
of your other coworkers, I agree that you are probably not someone incapable
of making friends. It could be that this coworker of yours just doesn’t want
to make any friends in the office. Maybe they are thinking about work when you
try to chat with them at the water cooler, and so their mind isn’t on your
conversation and they give you short replies. I think there are a million
possible reasons this person isn’t warming up to you. The real question I have
for you, is why does this bother you so much? It sounds like you’ve got a
group of your colleagues that you hang out with and are friends with. I’d
suggest you leave this guy alone, and let him do his own thing, and you can
talk to and hang out with your friends. You’ve made it clear you are willing
to be friendly with him, so he should have gotten the hint that you’re happy to
talk to or spend time with him if he so chooses. I think you have done all you
can do, and now it is up to your coworker to decide to engage in this
friendship if he wants one. Don’t stress about it, not everyone gets along as
fast friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relax!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;colleague-crush&quot;&gt;Colleague Crush&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So we had a new person join my company a few months ago, and he’s such a
great guy. I didn’t mean to, but I totally have a crush on him, and I’ve
tried to drop him hints by timing my coffee breaks to line up with his, and
joining him for lunch outside. The problem is, he doesn’t seem to have a
clue! I don’t want to do anything inappropriate or create an awkward
situation at work, so what should I do now? Can I confess my true feelings
for this guy?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Crushin’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crushin’,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds like you’re in a bit of a pickle for sure. I think you know what I’m
going to tell you, but it just isn’t what you want to hear. The best thing
you can do for your career, and to maintain your workplace environment, is to
drop it and stop pursuing this guy, no matter how careful you have been so far.
For all you know, you may be putting this guy in a very awkward position. He
might not be as clueless as you think, but doesn’t know how to politely reject
your advances and is instead trying to ignore them. If you can’t drop this, I
think you can certainly tell him how you feel. But if you go down that route
I think you should just be direct, and find a way to have that conversation
that isn’t awkward, regardless of what his answer is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Work" /><category term="Relationships" /><category term="Romance" /><summary type="html">Advice given on May 23, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-18</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-18" /><published>2022-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-18">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 18, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-scream&quot;&gt;I scream&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I see that you reside in Austin, TX. Very cool. I’m coming to visit Austin,
and wanted to get your suggestions for ice cream places to check out. From
what I can tell by looking at the weather forecasts it’s already gotten
quite warm over there, and I’m looking to stay cool and enjoy some ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I Scream For Ice Cream&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screamer,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, this is a pretty &lt;em&gt;chill&lt;/em&gt; question indeed. The “best” ice cream in town is
obviously a matter of opinion, and to be honest, I’ve yet to identify my
personal favorite. However, I can name my current top 3 picks, which are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilikelick.com/&quot;&gt;Lick&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://amysicecreams.com/&quot;&gt;Amy’s&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://jenis.com/&quot;&gt;Jeni’s&lt;/a&gt;. Of the three, I believe both Lick and Amy’s were
founded in Austin, while Jeni’s was started in Ohio. All worth checking out in
my humble opinion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay cool,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eating-on-the-run&quot;&gt;Eating on the Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So I’ve been starting to run farther distances than I used to, and I am
starting to get hungry on my runs. Do you think it’s weird to take a snack
and munch as I jog? What should I take to eat and drink on my runs? Any
thoughts or suggestions are appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Joggin’ and gobblin’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi Jogger,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting question. I can’t speak to what will work for you, but
I can tell you what my strategy for re-fueling mid-run used to be. I used to
plan to eat and drink for runs that were going to take longer than 1 hour.
Anything less than an hour I decided was short enough that I could wait until
the run was over to re-hydrate and eat. When I was going to eat on a run, I
think I tried to time it out so that I was having a bite and a sip of water
roughly every half an hour. This way I never had to eat or drink too much at
a time, and was also getting a more consistent supply of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d read online that because you lose a fair amount of salt when you sweat, it
can be good to drink something other than pure water. To be frugal, I used to
just add a little bit of salt to my water bottle to help replenish the salt I
was sweating out. You could also surely get powdered mixes, or sports drinks to
have during your jog. Food-wise, I used to eat raisins as they are high in
sugar, inexpensive, and will keep you energized. I could also imagine some
nuts would be tasty while running. There are, of course, the “goo” products
often sold to endurance athletes which are designed to provide the fuel you
need to continue your activity, although they are certainly more costly than
the simple raisin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck out there,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Health" /><category term="Exercise" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 18, 2022.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2022-04-12</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-12" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2022-04-12" /><published>2022-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/advice/advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/advice/2022-04-12">&lt;p&gt;Advice given on April 12, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-cookin&quot;&gt;What’s Cookin’?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey Jay,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I feel like I am eating out too often. I want to cook more at home, but
have trouble finding the time and the motivation. Even when I have the time
and want to cook, I often don’t know what to make. Any advice? I realize
eating out all the time probably isn’t the healthiest for my wallet or
for my health. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Chef-to-be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chef-to-be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, it sounds like you want to make some smart moves and I commend you for
that. I feel like this is something I’ve heard from various people over the
course of my life, and so hopefully that makes you feel better about this
issue you’re having. Step one to changing any undesired behavior is
acknowledging it and deciding you actually want to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how to change can pose it’s own set of challenges. You’ve pointed out
that it is likely healthier for you to cook your own meals, and is financially
a better move too. Remember to keep that in mind to help motivate yourself
to cook. It can also help to have some recipes you enjoy eating to motivate
yourself to make those meals. I suggest you try keeping your kitchen stocked
with fresh groceries, so that when you look in your fridge or pantry you see
ingredients you find appealing and can cook into tasty meals. Having the right
foods already at home may help you want to cook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think choosing what to make is an incredibly personal decision. It also comes
down to your individual skill in the kitchen, available ingredients,
kitchenware, and the amount of time you have to prepare a given meal. Given
these constraints, it might help you to start looking up various lists of
recipes, maybe group them by prep time. This way, you can quickly consult your
curated list when it is time to cook, and you won’t waste cooking time looking
up a recipe to make. If you do your research, this list of recipes may also
help guide your shopping at the grocery store, to ensure you always have some
of the common items you need to make your favorite dishes. You’ll also be able
to make a quick dish when pressed for time, or get involved in a longer cooking
process when you have the time to spare. I wish you the best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay hungry,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jayaram Hariharan</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Happiness" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Cooking" /><summary type="html">Advice given on April 12, 2022.</summary></entry></feed>